<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Dan Hicks </title>
<link>https://dhicks.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://dhicks.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Website description</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.13</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Is this how you think DEI works at colleges and universities? (rejected from r/AskTrumpSupporters)</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2025-02-26-DEI.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Bringing this question over from <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/nathanielcgreen.bsky.social/post/3liz5pbiges2f">Bluesky</a>, where I first saw it reposted. It’s based on a tweet (post?) on X by an account I don’t know.</p>
<p>Paraphrasing the tweet, “DEI is a novel bureaucracy that had been created within the college system, which represented neither the faculty nor the students, and it was starting to act like many faculty members’ direct supervisor and telling them how to teach.”</p>
<p>My question: Does this explanation fit with how you think DEI works at colleges and universities?</p>
<p>(Just to be clear, in my experience this is not at all how it works. I’m a college professor, a social scientist, and I’ve taught at six different schools over the past 20+ years. I’ve never had anyone audit my syllabus or tell me what I should or shouldn’t teach. A few years ago the faculty in my department did an exercise in diversifying the authors on our syllabi. This was entirely voluntary; we decided as a department to do it, some of us made no changes, and some of us made big changes. We’re interested in hiring someone who specializes in our field’s version of critical race theory, because our student body is majority Hispanic and they’re really interested in taking those classes. If we or the students had different priorities, we’d be trying to hire in another area instead. The DEI office at my current school mostly puts on events and organizes mentoring programs.)</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2025-02-26-DEI.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Weaponized metascience</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2025-01-14-weaponized-metascience.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A couple days ago, Senator Ted Cruz (R-TX) <a href="https://www.commerce.senate.gov/2025/2/cruz-led-investigation-uncovers-2-billion-in-woke-dei-grants-at-nsf-releases-full-database">released</a> a spreadsheet of about 3.5k “woke DEI grants” made by NSF. This spreadsheet was the basis for <a href="https://www.commerce.senate.gov/services/files/4BD2D522-2092-4246-91A5-58EEF99750BC">a report</a> released last October by the minority of the Senate Commerce, Science, and Transportation committee (of which Cruz was the minority chair). Congressional Republicans have a long history of complaining that NSF funds “wasteful” or “silly” projects, and this report and spreadsheet continue that tradition, using the anti-DEI framing that happens to be popular today.</p>
<p>As a computational social scientist and philosopher of science, one thing that struck me about the report was a “methods section,” a pair of appendices that narrated the text mining methods used by congressional staff to assemble the list of awards and apply labels such as “social justice.” Staff used “N-gram analysis” to find “the most-often-used terms and phrases” across about 30,000 NSF award abstracts, then “parsed those terms for DEI keywords and phrases,” “using over 800,000 variations and combinations.” The second appendix is a series of term lists — one for each of the five labels — with a total of about 750 words or short phrases. The authors of the report used multiple rounds of filtering, “a categorization ‘qualifier’ tagging formula in Excel,” and three rounds of manual review, to arrive at the final list of about 3.5k awards and the five labels.</p>
<p>At this level of description, the methods used to assemble this report are similar to methods my research group uses in our own text mining projects. For example, in a paper currently under review, using the fulltext of tens of thousands of journal articles we trace the presence of race science across mainstream and fringe scientific journals over the second half of the twentieth century. Such work is often grouped under the interdisciplinary heading of “metascience,” utilizing scientific methods to better understand scientific research processes and communities.</p>
<p>In this sense, Senator Cruz is engaged in <strong>weaponized metascience</strong>: using metascience in an attempt to undermine the political and cultural standing of scientific research.</p>
<p>Like congressional complaints about NSF, weaponized metascience is not new. During the first Trump administration, the Environmental Protection Agency proposed (and briefly adopted) a rule, originally called “Strengthening Transparency in Regulatory Science,” that appealed to concerns about a widespread replication crisis and the open science movement in an effort to undermine the use of public health research at the agency. Numerous scientists and advocacy organizations criticized the rule as “anti-science,” without noting that it appealed to widespread sentiments within the scientific community itself <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksWhenVirtuesAre2022 HicksOpenScienceReplication2023">(D. J. Hicks 2022b, 2023)</span>.</p>
<hr>
<p>It should not be surprising that the quality of weaponized metascience is often low by the standards of academic research. In text mining, one way to avoid “false positives” is to filter out documents that only match a single keyword. This filter is idempotent, meaning that it has no effect after being run once: all of the single-match documents are removed on the first pass. Nonetheless, the “methods section” of the Cruz report says that this filter was applied twice, at two different stages of review. The first pass removed 3,118 awards; and, somehow, the second removed 5,715. At best, this is a serious misreporting error, perhaps if the second pass involved a much larger keyword list; at worst it indicates a severe error in the analysis scripts.</p>
<p>The report also makes claims that these methods, and the resulting database, cannot possibly support. For example, the report claims that “Instead of identifying the best or most talented scientists, NSF funded researchers who prioritized filling out research teams and programs based on ethnicity, cultural background, or political perspectives.”</p>
<p>Most of the researchers funded by NSF grants — students, postdoctoral researchers, professional research staff — are hired by the universities that receive the awards, not NSF. Some personnel are named in the initial grant application, but otherwise universities don’t notify NSF who they hire using NSF-awarded funds, much less report them for release in a public database. The particular data portal used by Cruz’ staff does not even contain the names of the primary investigator for each award (though these names are available through NSF’s award search portal). And, of course, even if Cruz’ staff did somehow know the <em>names</em> of the members of the research teams, they still wouldn’t know their qualifications, ethnicity, cultural backgrounds, or political perspectives, much less what role these factors played in the hiring decisions.</p>
<p>Similarly, a distinguished statistician — a fellow of both the American Statistical Association and the American Association for the Advancement of Science, and a member of EPA’s Science Advisory Board during the first Trump administration — published numerous papers using a fundamentally flawed statistical methodology <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuePlotDoes2022">(D. J. Hicks 2022a)</span>. Many of these papers claimed to show that research misconduct was widespread in air pollution epidemiology. At least some were funded by the American Petroleum Institute <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksYoungsPValuePlot2022">(D. Hicks 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>As a final example, recently the Trump administration attempted to unilaterally impose a cap of 15% on indirect costs for NIH-funded awards. Reporters at Wired <span class="citation" data-cites="ReynoldsNIHFundingCuts">(Reynolds n.d.)</span> traced this policy to a <a href="https://www.heritage.org/education/report/indirect-costs-how-taxpayers-subsidize-university-nonsense">report</a> by two affiliates of the Heritage Foundation, which alleged that indirect costs were used to “subsidize the agenda of the political left through funding its research agendas and Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion (DEI) staff on university campuses.” The primary evidence for this claim was a collection of simple univariable regressions of the number of “DEI staff” against indirect costs for 82 universities. The authors of the report made no effort whatsoever to adjust for potential confounders in this regression — despite the lead author being a former Distinguished Professor and education researcher at the University of Arkansas.</p>
<hr>
<p>But the low quality of weaponized metascience is beside the point. The purpose of weaponized metascience is to <em>appear</em> scientific, to adopt the trappings of science in order to discredit science. Over the past 150 years or so, our society has become deeply “scientistic,” holding up science (or things that look like science) as the best and most reliable source of knowledge. Science and its defenders need to understand that, by and large, the contemporary far right and its allies are not interested in challenging this scientism. Project 2025 doesn’t say anything about replacing evolution with intelligent design in schools, for example. Instead the goal is to turn science into a tool of their political and cultural project, dominated by conservative, nationalistic, straight white men. To Make Science Great Again.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-HicksYoungsPValuePlot2022" class="csl-entry">
Hicks, Dan. 2022. <span>“Young’s P-Value Plot as an Agnogenic Technique, Dan Hicks.”</span> Social Epistemology Review and Reply Collective. March 16, 2022. <a href="https://social-epistemology.com/2022/03/16/youngs-p-value-plot-as-an-agnogenic-technique-dan-hicks/">https://social-epistemology.com/2022/03/16/youngs-p-value-plot-as-an-agnogenic-technique-dan-hicks/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksValuePlotDoes2022" class="csl-entry">
Hicks, Daniel J. 2022a. <span>“The P Value Plot Does Not Provide Evidence Against Air Pollution Hazards.”</span> <em>Environmental Epidemiology</em> 6 (2): e198. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1097/EE9.0000000000000198">https://doi.org/10.1097/EE9.0000000000000198</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksWhenVirtuesAre2022" class="csl-entry">
———. 2022b. <span>“When Virtues are Vices: <span>‘Anti-Science’</span> Epistemic Values in Environmental Politics.”</span> <em>Philosophy, Theory, and Practice in Biology</em> 14 (0). <a href="https://doi.org/10.3998/.2629">https://doi.org/10.3998/.2629</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksOpenScienceReplication2023" class="csl-entry">
———. 2023. <span>“Open Science, the Replication Crisis, and Environmental Public Health.”</span> <em>Accountability in Research</em> 30 (1): 34–62. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/08989621.2021.1962713">https://doi.org/10.1080/08989621.2021.1962713</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ReynoldsNIHFundingCuts" class="csl-entry">
Reynolds, Matt. n.d. <span>“NIH Funding Cuts Appear to Draw on Heritage Foundation Report That Blasts <span>‘DEI Staff’</span>.”</span> <em>Wired</em>. Accessed February 11, 2025. <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/nih-indirect-funding-cuts-heritage-foundation/">https://www.wired.com/story/nih-indirect-funding-cuts-heritage-foundation/</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2025-01-14-weaponized-metascience.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Weaponizing Value Freedom in Defense of Race Science</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-12-22-weaponizing-value-freedom.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The aim of this blog post is to illustrate the ways value freedom is weaponized in defense of race science by <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span>.</p>
<p>Following the definitions in <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksRaceScienceMainstream2024">Hicks and Lobato (2024)</span>, I understand <em>scientific racism</em> as the social practice of purporting to justify racial inequality and colonialism by appealing to the epistemic authority of science. And <em>race science</em> refers to scientific and/or pseudoscientific research, including research products (journal articles, etc.), that can be utilized for scientific racism.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> is one of a pair of articles replying to <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span>. <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> offer a critique of <em>racial hereditarianism research</em> (RHR), which they characterize as research products that</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>claim that folk racial classifications are biologically meaningful categories and that racial differences in intelligence test scores, educational attainment, income, and crime partly or even primarily originate from genetic differences between races. (497)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I understand RHR as a specific line of race science.</p>
<p>A real paper would give more context to the exchange of papers between these two groups of authors here.</p>
<p>I argue that <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> weaponize value-freedom in a number of ways (to be discussed below), claiming that <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> violate value-freedom and therefore their critique of RHR/race science can be dismissed.</p>
<p>I first make some preliminary remarks on value-freedom, as I use the term here. Next I assess <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span>’s appeal to Robert Merton’s norms of science. I discuss the importance of implicature in the relationship between race science and scientific racism, and conclude by reflecting on the way a “value freedom tu quoque” are used to deflect charges of violating value freedom.</p>
<section id="value-freedom" class="level1">
<h1>Value freedom</h1>
<p>In this post, I use the term “value freedom,” rather than the more common term in philosophy of science, “the value-free ideal” or VFI. Philosophers’ understanding of VFI has a narrow scope: it prohibits only the influence of non-epistemic values in a particular “core,” “epistemic” “stage” of scientific inquiry. <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> do not appear to use such a narrowly-scoped idea; instead they appeal to a conceptual separation between research and its application and the political motivations of their interlocutors independent of “stages” of inquiry.</p>
<p>These ideas — VFI, the research/application distinction, and motivations in general — are related, but logically distinct. <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> do not appeal to VFI, in the strict sense; but they do appeal to a cluster of related ideas, that can be usefully grouped under the general heading of “value freedom.”</p>
<p>The research/application distinction can be seen in the way <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> respond to the argument that the Buffalo mass shooter’s cited race science research in his manifesto. They argue that this critique is “somewhat like demanding that chemistry be outlawed and its practitioners smeared as having blood on their hands, just because some terrorists use chemistry to make poisons or explosives that kill people” (2).<sup>1</sup> Later, they provide quotations from earlier papers that recognize “that more must be done to avoid politicized misuse of socially salient research” because “a tendency for some of our ideas to be misappropriated by highly politically motivated individuals online,” and so “we have failed to make sufficient efforts to clearly disconnect our work from political ideologies” (4). In the immediately following paragraph, they complain that “despite this apparent candor and restraint, such researchers somehow still are cast as shouldering responsibility whenever some disturbed individual misappropriates some of their ideas” (4).</p>
<p>In these passages, <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> separate race science research from its (harmful) downstream application. The chemical weapons analogy and the final quotation from page 4 claim that race scientists are not responsible for these applications. The “failed to make sufficient efforts” quotation accepts responsibility — but apparently only for insufficient value freedom <em>within</em> their research. Their responsibility does not extend to the distinct act of “misappropriat[ion].”<sup>2</sup></p>
<p>Near the end of §3, <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> claim that “BJ&amp;W’s real motivation is their political ideology … rather than any balanced appraisal of the costs and benefits to society of” race science (3). From here, they assert that race science is opposed because it “contradict[s] the sacred values of political groups,” evoke the Lysenko affair, claim that “the radical left” does not distinguish between “RHR, genetics, evolutionary psychology, eugenics, systemic racism and sexism, IQ testing, and, indeed, Mertonian norms of science themselves,” and conclude that <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span>’s policy proposals would lead down a slippery slope to broad censorship (4-5). This line of thought alleges that <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> are violating value freedom, but not (merely) in the “core” stage of gathering evidence and evaluating hypotheses, i.e., within the scope of VFI. The violation appears to be either holding left-wing values itself or — to be charitable to <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> — perhaps using left-wing values as premises in policy arguments.</p>
</section>
<section id="mertonian-and-anti-mertonian-norms" class="level1">
<h1>Mertonian and Anti-Mertonian Norms</h1>
<p>The title and §1 claim that <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> are proposing to replace the “Mertonian norms” — the “ethos of science” described by sociologist Robert Merton — with a set of “anti-Mertonian norms.”</p>
<p>If this were a real paper, I would summarize the “anti-Mertonian norms” here. I would also note that <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> misquote <span class="citation" data-cites="MertonNoteScienceDemocracy1942">Robert K. Merton (1942)</span> (121), renaming the norm of communism as “communality.”</p>
<p>The appeal to Merton to defend value freedom is ironic, because Merton presented the “ethos of science” as an explicitly ideological argument against fascism — especially in Germany, and especially race science — and for liberal democracy <span class="citation" data-cites="MertonScienceSocialOrder1938 MertonNoteScienceDemocracy1942">(Robert K. Merton 1938; Robert K. Merton 1942)</span>.<sup>3</sup></p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> cite <span class="citation" data-cites="MitroffNormsCounterNormsSelect1974">Mitroff (1974)</span> as a reference for the concept of “anti-norms” (Mitroff’s term is “counter-norms”) but miss the significance of not only Mitroff’s paper but also Merton’s later work on norms of science as summarized on the first few pages of Mitroff’s paper. In Merton’s later work, in any complex social practice such as science, the “dominant [norms] alone would not be flexible enough to provide for the endlessly varying contingencies of social relations” <span class="citation" data-cites="MitroffNormsCounterNormsSelect1974">(Merton and Barber as quoted by Mitroff 1974, 579)</span>. Contrasting, “subsidiary counter-norms” develop to enable this necessary flexibility. For example, sociologists and philosophers — including Merton himself — have long recognized that, along with and in contrast to communism, scientists are often motivated by self-interest, chasing credit and prestige, under the “priority rule” that the first to publish a significant new discovery receives all the credit for it <span class="citation" data-cites="StrevensRolePriorityRule2003">(Strevens and Journal of Philosophy, Inc. 2003)</span>.</p>
<p>In this light, even as characterized by <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span>, the “counter-norms” proposed by <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> can be seen as giving useful flexibility to an excessively narrow reading of Merton’s norms:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>secrecy</em> recognizes that some scientific evidence or even findings are too sensitive and potentially dangerous to publish (locations of endangered species that might be targeted by poachers; Indigenous sacred sites that also carry Traditional Ecological Knowledge; instructions for producing weapons of mass destruction)</li>
<li><em>particularism</em> recognizes that the work of scientific bad actors should receive, at a minimum, heightened scrutiny (individuals who have committed serious research misconduct; cranks who refuse to respect the uptake norm requiring response to criticism)</li>
<li><em>interested</em> recognizes that, when scientific research carries elevated risk for harmful downstream social consequences, it is appropriate to require a more demanding standard of evidence <span class="citation" data-cites="KitcherArgumentFreeInquiry1997 HavstadSensationalScienceArchaic2021 MeyerWrestlingSocialBehavioral2023">(Kitcher 1997; Havstad 2021; Meyer et al. 2023)</span></li>
<li><em>organized dogmatism</em> designates certain questions as so thoroughly studied and rival research programs so degenerate <span class="citation" data-cites="LakatosFalsificationMethodologyScientific2004">(Lakatos 2004)</span> that there is no expected value in continuing to regard those questions as open and those rival research programs as pursuitworthy (anthropogenic climate change)</li>
</ul>
<p>In other words, taking the Mertonian norms as the exclusive norms for a scientific community would be corrosive, as it would leave the community vulnerable to cranks, fraudsters, and merchants of doubt.</p>
<p>Both Merton’s norms and the “<span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> counter-norms” require the exercise of judgment. When exactly does a norm apply, what exactly does it require or prohibit, and how should it be balanced against other, conflicting norms? Scientists are likely to disagree about such questions, and scientific communities must necessarily engage in internal politics to establish the bounds of reasonable disagreement over the answers. Both <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> should be read as salvos in a political conflict unfolding within contemporary psychology.</p>
</section>
<section id="implicature-and-the-denial-of-responsibility" class="level1">
<h1>Implicature and the Denial of Responsibility</h1>
<p>The concept of implicature was developed by the philosopher of language Paul Grice to characterize the way in which language often communicates meaning beyond its explicit content and strict deductive entailments. An example comes from §1 of <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> itself. At no point do <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> say explicitly that the “anti-Mertonian norms” they attribute to <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> will be corrosive, destructive, or otherwise bad. Instead, they argue that the Mertonian norms “embody centuries of research experience, and reflect a long-established consensus among academic scientists about ways of doing research that tend to promote the highest rate of scientific progress” (2). Taken literally, this argument does not entail anything whatsoever about the “anti-Mertonian norms”; strictly speaking, it is logically irrelevant to the latter norms. But the implicature is that the latter norms will tradition, reject consensus, and will frustrate rather than promote scientific progress.<sup>4</sup></p>
<p>Implicature is crucial to the phenomenon of racial dogwhistles. Phrases like “wolf pack” and “welfare mothers” do not explicitly refer or deductively entail anything about African Americans, and thus allow their users to deflect charges of racism. But in the US political context these phrases readily communicate pernicious stereotypes that young Black men are dangerous, subhuman criminals and Black women are lazy abusers of the social safety net.</p>
<p>Implicature is context-dependent. These particular racial dogwhistles are likely to be less effective outside the US.</p>
<p>Implicature can also be independent of the speaker’s communicative intent. Someone can invoke racial stereotypes without realizing they are doing so, and indeed even when they would explicitly reject these stereotypes.</p>
<p>I propose that implicature is often what connects race science to scientific racism. A piece of research can be taken up and used to purportedly justify racial inequality <em>not</em> because of the researcher’s own racist intentions (indeed, they might explicitly denounce such intentions) or its explicit conclusions (indeed, the research might not say anything explicit about race at all) but because <em>in a certain context</em> it is amenable to being interpreted as providing such a justification. <span class="citation" data-cites="WillsAreClustersRaces2017">(For analysis of an example from human genomics, see Wills 2017.)</span></p>
<p>The idea of “misuse” or “misappropriation” is crucial to the way <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> deny responsibility for scientific racist use of race science research, as in their responses to the Buffalo shooter manifesto. “Misuse” appears six times in the five-page paper, and “misappropriation” three times (all on page 4).</p>
<p>But implicature significantly complicates the idea of “misuse” or “misappropriation” of scientific research. Because implicature extends beyond the speaker’s intention, a simplistic conception of misuse — in terms of how a researcher intended their research to be used — is inapt, and provides the same rhetorical cover that dogwhistles provide race-baiting politicians and “just asking questions” provides conspiracy theorists.<sup>5</sup> A more robust approach might come from the law of torts, and the notion of “reasonable foresight,” that is, whether a “reasonable scientist” could have foreseen this application of their research and its consequences <span class="citation" data-cites="DouglasSciencePolicyValuefree2009">(Douglas 2009 ch.&nbsp;4)</span>. As with norms and counter-norms, the bounds of what counts as a “reasonable scientist” and what they can foresee are necessarily a political issue.</p>
<p>Again, implicatures are context-dependent, and <span class="citation" data-cites="KitcherArgumentFreeInquiry1997">Kitcher (1997)</span> identified some key features of contemporary Anglophone societies that support scientific racist implicatures. Briefly, these features are asymmetries in the uptake of racial differences research: research that supports scientific racism will be taken up and the degree of support exaggerated, while research that challenges scientific racism will be rejected (not taken up) and its degree of challenge downplayed.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> claim that <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span>’s proposals would “backfire” with three kinds of “unintended consequences” (3): blocking research that uncovers evidence supporting “racial environmentalist hypotheses”; blocking research that challenges views that circulate among white nationalists,<sup>6</sup> and third, these proposals “would also apply very broadly to all of ‘mainstream human genetics’” (4).</p>
<p>The first two unintended consequences founder on Kitcher’s asymmetries. Insofar as they obtain, both kinds of research would tend to be rejected and their degree of challenge to scientific racism downplayed.</p>
<p>In addition, both kinds of research carry scientific racist implicatures, namely, that it is an open and scientifically legitimate possibility that there is a “natural” racial hierarchy based on differences in “innate” ability. Even research that is intended to undermine racial hierarchy, is expected to produce evidence challenging scientific racism, and actually does produce such evidence, assumes that the question of “natural” racial hierarchy remains unanswered.</p>
</section>
<section id="weaponizing-value-freedom-to-deflect-charges-of-violating-value-freedom" class="level1">
<h1>Weaponizing value freedom to deflect charges of violating value freedom</h1>
<p>A core element of <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span>’s critique is that race science promotes the pernicious and morally noxious worldview of scientific racism. This critique does not need to assume value freedom: one can regard scientific racism as pernicious and morally noxious without assume that science should be, in some general sense or another, value free. But it can be read through the lens of value freedom: race science promotes non-neutral values and therefore race science should be avoided. <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> occasionally use something like this framing: “we dispute claims of ‘value neutrality’ for this research” (498); “These conclusions are not value-free or ideologically neutral” (499).</p>
<p>A major thread of <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span>’s reply is a tu quoque that <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> have violated value freedom, in the ways discussed above. This argument strategy has a long history in responses to critiques that science promotes racism, sexism, or other forms of injustice. In the “science wars” of the 1990s it was used against feminist critiques of sexist science <span class="citation" data-cites="LloydObjectivityDoubleStandard1995 LloydScienceAntiScienceObjectivity1997">(E. A. Lloyd 1995; E. Lloyd 1997)</span>. It is deployed today in rants that claim DEI initiatives undermine “merit in science.”</p>
<p>Such arguments are often logically irrelevant, in two ways. First, they do not provide any reason or evidence to think that race scientists have not violated value freedom. Even if we accept that <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston (2024)</span> violated value freedom, this does not give us a reason to think that, say, Richard Lynn did not violate value freedom. Second, these arguments are often made against interlocutors who do not accept value freedom, do think that science should necessarily be value free. (The difference between rejecting race science on the basis of value freedom and rejecting it on the basis of antiracist values.) So the tu quoque does not show that the interlocutor is being inconsistent or hypocritical, endorsing a principle while also violating it.</p>
<p>These arguments often have other problems, like the ones I’ve identified here: based on a superficial misreading of source material, applied inconsistently or without thinking through the logical implications of a position, and so on.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, these arguments can be rhetorically effective, insofar as they shift the focus of debate from race science to its critics, DARVO-style, and insofar as the audience does accept value freedom and consequently regards the critics as discredited and not worth engaging. And many scientists and members of the general public do think that science should be value free.</p>
<p>In this sense, these arguments weaponize value freedom to deflect charges of violations of value freedom.</p>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024" class="csl-entry">
Bird, Kevin A., John P. Jackson Jr., and Andrew S. Winston. 2024. <span>“Confronting Scientific Racism in Psychology: Lessons from Evolutionary Biology and Genetics.”</span> <em>American Psychologist</em> 79 (4): 497–508. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/amp0001228">https://doi.org/10.1037/amp0001228</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-DouglasSciencePolicyValuefree2009" class="csl-entry">
Douglas, Heather E. 2009. <em>Science, Policy, and the Value-Free Ideal</em>. Pittsburgh, Pa: University of Pittsburgh Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-HavstadSensationalScienceArchaic2021" class="csl-entry">
Havstad, Joyce C. 2021. <span>“Sensational Science, Archaic Hominin Genetics, and Amplified Inductive Risk.”</span> <em>Canadian Journal of Philosophy</em>, July, 1–26. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/can.2021.15">https://doi.org/10.1017/can.2021.15</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksRaceScienceMainstream2024" class="csl-entry">
Hicks, Daniel, and Emilio Jon Christopher Lobato. 2024. <span>“Race Science in Mainstream Psychology, 1960-2010.”</span> OSF. <a href="https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/y8hr3">https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/y8hr3</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-KitcherArgumentFreeInquiry1997" class="csl-entry">
Kitcher, Philip. 1997. <span>“An Argument About Free Inquiry.”</span> <em>Noûs</em> 31 (3): 279–306. <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2216207">https://www.jstor.org/stable/2216207</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LakatosFalsificationMethodologyScientific2004" class="csl-entry">
Lakatos, I. 2004. <span>“Falsification and the Methodology of Scientific Research Programmes.”</span> <em>Karl Popper: Critical Assessments of Leading Philosophers</em>. <a href="http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;id=yajVRpMVzLgC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA295-IA9&amp;dq=%22lakatos%22+%22scientific+research+programmes%22&amp;ots=nV87et3QUT&amp;sig=DwK1x8Gvh1tOFiR-LZ694ihXNl8">http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;id=yajVRpMVzLgC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA295-IA9&amp;dq=%22lakatos%22+%22scientific+research+programmes%22&amp;ots=nV87et3QUT&amp;sig=DwK1x8Gvh1tOFiR-LZ694ihXNl8</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LloydScienceAntiScienceObjectivity1997" class="csl-entry">
Lloyd, Elisabeth. 1997. <span>“Science and Anti-Science: Objectivity and Its Enemies.”</span> In <em>Feminism, Science, and the Philosophy of Science</em>, edited by Lynn Hankinson Nelson and Jack Nelson. Springer. <a href="http://books.google.ca/books?id=dbrQ4R7zWpwC&amp;pg=PA121&amp;dq=intitle:FEMINISM+SCIENCE+AND+THE+PHILOSOPHY+OF+SCIEN&amp;hl=&amp;cd=1&amp;source=gbs_api">http://books.google.ca/books?id=dbrQ4R7zWpwC&amp;pg=PA121&amp;dq=intitle:FEMINISM+SCIENCE+AND+THE+PHILOSOPHY+OF+SCIEN&amp;hl=&amp;cd=1&amp;source=gbs_api</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LloydObjectivityDoubleStandard1995" class="csl-entry">
Lloyd, Elisabeth A. 1995. <span>“Objectivity and the Double Standard for Feminist Epistemologies.”</span> <em>Synthese</em> 104 (3): 351–81. <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/20117438">http://www.jstor.org/stable/20117438</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-MertonScienceSocialOrder1938" class="csl-entry">
Merton, Robert K. 1938. <span>“Science and the Social Order.”</span> <em>Philosophy of Science</em> 5 (3): 321–37. <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/184838">http://www.jstor.org/stable/184838</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-MertonNoteScienceDemocracy1942" class="csl-entry">
Merton, Robert K. 1942. <span>“A Note on Science and Democracy.”</span> <em>Journal of Legal and Political Sociology</em> 1: 115. <a href="http://heinonline.org/HOL/Page?handle=hein.journals/jolegpo1&amp;id=115&amp;div=10&amp;collection=usjournals">http://heinonline.org/HOL/Page?handle=hein.journals/jolegpo1&amp;id=115&amp;div=10&amp;collection=usjournals</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-MeyerWrestlingSocialBehavioral2023" class="csl-entry">
Meyer, Michelle N., Paul S. Appelbaum, Daniel J. Benjamin, Shawneequa L. Callier, Nathaniel Comfort, Dalton Conley, Jeremy Freese, et al. 2023. <span>“Wrestling with Social and Behavioral Genomics: Risks, Potential Benefits, and Ethical Responsibility.”</span> <em>Hastings Center Report</em> 53 (S1): S2–49. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/hast.1477">https://doi.org/10.1002/hast.1477</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-MitroffNormsCounterNormsSelect1974" class="csl-entry">
Mitroff, Ian I. 1974. <span>“Norms and Counter-Norms in a Select Group of the Apollo Moon Scientists: A Case Study of the Ambivalence of Scientists.”</span> <em>American Sociological Review</em> 39 (4): 579–95. <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2094423">http://www.jstor.org/stable/2094423</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-StrevensRolePriorityRule2003" class="csl-entry">
Strevens, Michael, and Journal of Philosophy, Inc. 2003. <span>“The Role of the Priority Rule in Science:”</span> <em>Journal of Philosophy</em> 100 (2): 55–79. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5840/jphil2003100224">https://doi.org/10.5840/jphil2003100224</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-WillsAreClustersRaces2017" class="csl-entry">
Wills, Melissa. 2017. <span>“Are Clusters Races? A Discussion of the Rhetorical Appropriation of Rosenberg Et Al.’s <span>‘Genetic Structure of Human Populations’</span>.”</span> <em>Philosophy &amp; Theory in Biology</em> 9. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3998/ptb.6959004.0009.012">https://doi.org/10.3998/ptb.6959004.0009.012</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025" class="csl-entry">
Woodley Of Menie, Michael A., Mateo Peñaherrera-Aguirre, Aurelio-José Figueredo, Geoffrey F. Miller, Thomas R. Coyle, Noah Carl, Fróði Debes, et al. 2025. <span>“Anti-Mertonian Norms Undermine the Scientific Ethos: A Critique of Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston’s Policy Proposals and Associated Justification.”</span> <em>Intelligence</em> 108 (January): 101879. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.intell.2024.101879">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.intell.2024.101879</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Notably, the American Chemical Society has a page on chemical weapons research that explicitly calls for national and international regulation on such research and the manufacture and circulation of potentially dangerous materials: <a href="https://www.acs.org/policy/publicpolicies/science-policy/preventing-chemical-weapons.html" class="uri">https://www.acs.org/policy/publicpolicies/science-policy/preventing-chemical-weapons.html</a>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>This distinction — and the consequent denial of responsibility for application — is applied inconsistently. Shortly after the chemical weapons analogy, <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> offer a second, tu quoque reply: “BJ&amp;W do not discuss cases in which left-wing scholarship, beliefs, and research may have influenced violent criminals” (2).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>It’s an interesting question whether Merton ever said anything about the Lysenko affair, which peaked starting in 1948.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Note the irony that <span class="citation" data-cites="WoodleyOfMenieAntiMertonianNormsUndermine2025">Woodley Of Menie et al. (2025)</span> are attempting to challenge “organized dogmatism” by appeal to tradition and consensus, and defend universalism by appeal to the judgment of the select group of “academic scientists.”↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>“RHR proponents often assert that no racial inferiority is implied by claims of evolved smaller brains, lower intelligence, and greater propensity for violence in people of African descent, and therefore such claims are not ‘racist’ (see Carl, 2019, p.&nbsp;271; Gottfredson, 2013)” <span class="citation" data-cites="BirdConfrontingScientificRacism2024">(Bird, Jackson Jr., and Winston 2024, 505)</span>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>The example given is evidence that Ashkenazi Jews have a greater average IQ than non-Jewish individuals of European descent and that this purportedly explains the “disproportionate Jewish influence in politics, finance, science, and media” (3).↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-12-22-weaponizing-value-freedom.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How I’m handling LLMs (Fall 2024 edition)</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-12-17-LLMs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>With the Fall term wrapping up in Northern American higher ed, a lot of my fellow humanities professors are reflecting on the way they feel forced to change their writing assignments to respond to LLMs. A lot of people are moving to only doing in-class writing — and bemoaning the loss of longer, more involved paper assignments.</p>
<p>This semester I taught an upper-division undergrad course that satisfied a “Writing in the Discipline” GE requirement, for which students are supposed to write roughly 5,000 words. So, to pass the class with a B,<sup>1</sup> this semester my students needed to write four short papers (highly structured, 4 paragraphs, 300-400 words each), revise two of those short papers based on my feedback, revise and expand one into a mid-length paper (about 1k words), and then revise and expand it again into a “full paper” (about 2k words). To get an A, in addition they needed to either write a second mid-length paper or submit a draft of the “full paper” about a month early for an extra round of feedback and revision.</p>
<p>None of this writing was done in class. Out of 24 students, I had one who used an LLM in a way that violated the class LLM policy, and that was on a single assignment. Perhaps there are a few more that I’ve missed; but I’m not seeing “they’re all cheating!” like some of my colleagues are reporting.</p>
<p>The purpose of this post is to document what I did. Maybe I got lucky? Maybe it won’t work in the future? Or maybe it’ll work for you too?</p>
<p>First, I had the students read <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/13afWz7Nw5zRL8abad4aZJM9vCCluaPus/view">a pair of essays on the value of first drafts</a>.<sup>2</sup> The first is Anne Lamont’s “Messy First Drafts,” from the ’90s; the second is a recent blog post that references the first and argues against using an LLM to write the first draft of a paper. (In the future, I plan to include <a href="https://prodev.illinoisstate.edu/ai/usage/">this taxonomy of LLM usage</a> as part of the assigned reading.)</p>
<p>Second, I <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1GbOOTYEB0G4W5dkCnbkFOOUPMH-BEopfc22OZKpX8Ng/edit?tab=t.0">anonymously collected students’ experience and thoughts on LLMs</a>. I think anonymity was important for candor here. In class, we discussed the two essays, and I had them read and react to another student’s anonymous paragraph.</p>
<p>Third, I had the students determine our class LLM policy. The taxonomy I linked up above was really helpful for structuring this discussion and the resulting policy. The class deliberated in small groups, then collectively, and voted to accept the policy for each potential use. There was some good debate over “brainstorming” and the exact wording for “co-create and revise.” The vote was generally unanimous; for one or two levels a couple-three were opposed. This was the result, as added to the syllabus:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In October, the class discussed the use of LLMs (large language models, such as ChatGPT) on course assignments. Using this taxonomy, we deliberated and voted to adopt the following policy. Violations are a form of academic misconduct.</p>
<ol start="0" type="1">
<li><p><strong>No use:</strong> Always permitted, except when a particular assignment explicitly requires use of a LLM. Except for those assignments, you’re never required to use a LLM in any way.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Organizational:</strong> Permitted, but you’re encouraged to check the LLM output for accuracy.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Brainstorming:</strong> Permitted only for developing the “big picture” of an assignment. You’re also encouraged to check the LLM output for accuracy.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Feedback:</strong> Permitted, but you must explicitly state that you used the LLM and note how.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Co-create and revise:</strong> Depends on how the LLM is used to co-create and revise your work. For developing an outline, you may use the section headings and overall structure, but not further details that the LLM provides, such as a suggested thesis or argument. For drafting the paper, LLM use is prohibited.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Unrestricted, attributed:</strong> Generally prohibited. Some particular assignments may explicitly permit or require using a LLM.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Unrestricted, unattributed:</strong> Always prohibited.</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Personally, I would not have permitted “brainstorming” or the outline-development use under “co-create and revise.” But I suspect respecting their autonomy — literally! — was important for the (apparent) high rate of compliance.</p>
<p>Fourth, each writing assignment had to include a wrapper, which among other things asked what resources were used on the paper, how they were used, and which was most useful. The resources included things like meeting 1-1 with me, the Writing Center, and Grammarly, along with an LLM. Grammarly is extremely popular; most of my students reported using it. Only a few students reported using an LLM, and most often it was to help summarize a reading or other source (which falls under “organizational” use).</p>
<p>The only violation I identified and acted upon happened a couple of weeks after the class formulated their policy. The fifth thing I did was handle this as a learning opportunity rather than the first stage of a disciplinary process. I asked the student to meet with me, and started by saying that I didn’t want this to become a disciplinary process. We talked about how they had used the LLM on the paper, and the stylistic telltales that made me suspect the policy had been violated. In particular, I explained how ChatGPT is very good at using sophisticated vocabulary and complex grammar to make very generic, shallow points. It’s not very insightful, and can’t put together a very compelling argument by philosophical standards. These points seemed to be well-taken. We also reviewed the LLM policy, and I reminded them of some elements of the class discussion behind it. After about 15 minutes of discussion, the student agreed that they had violated the policy, and accepted my offer to rewrite the paper from scratch. They did so, I gave them full credit, and we were able to move on.</p>
<p>More generally, I think it’s important to avoid an antagonistic relationship with my students. In my view, academic misconduct has two primary causes: the intense demands on students’ time and mental health; and a purely credentialist attitude towards education, that is, an attitude that the sole value of education is a formal credential (and not even instrumentally useful skills). Increased surveillance and threats likely exacerbate the demands on students and further alienate them from their coursework. This means they’re more rather than less likely to engage in misconduct. On the other hand, accommodating students’ needs and getting them to reflect on skills like writing a first draft likely reduce the chances of misconduct.</p>
<p>This approach requires being comfortable with “false negatives,” students who engage in misconduct — say, having ChatGPT write their papers from scratch — but aren’t caught and disciplined. Here I like the adage “You can lead a horse to water but you can’t make them drink.” Students who engage in misconduct in my classes are likely either struggling with major personal crises or have become irremediably cynical about the value of education. In both cases, they’re beyond my ability to help. That’s a sad and frustrating realization, but it’s one that allows me to devote my time and attention to teaching rather than prosecuting misconduct cases.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>A couple years ago, I switched to primarily effort-based grading, and generally only give two grades, A or B.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>“Right, like they’d actually do the reading.” I might need to write a post about this sometime, but I run my upper-division courses off of slides that students create before class meets. This has been very effective at getting them to do the reading.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-12-17-LLMs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The parable of fire ecology</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-11-08-fire-ecology.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>On Wednesday, after the election, I experienced a minor depressive episode: anhedonia, insomnia, loss of appetite, GI weirdness. I cleared the few remaining things on my schedule and went up to Ahwahne — Yosemite Valley — for the day. In my Environmental Philosophy and Politics class, we’ve been talking a fair amount about prescribed burning, and even took a field trip to Yosemite NP a few weeks ago to examine the fire landscape of the park in person. This inspired the following parable.</em></p>
<p>We Californians live in a landscape that is prone to catastrophic megafires. This was not intentional. No one set about trying to make our forest ecosystems as fire-prone as possible. Indeed, the intention was the opposite: to eliminate fire, in order to maximize the exploitation of the land for people and profit (with a subtle but very real emphasis on the second part). But it turns out that a landscape that’s very suitable for intense exploitation is also very suitable for intense conflagration.</p>
<p>The good news is that this problem is fixable. We can restore the landscape, cleaning up the accumulated debris and ladder fuels that turn ordinary sparks and healthy low-intensity fires into mass destruction events. We don’t necessarily understand all of the things that we need to do. But some initial steps are pretty clear.</p>
<p>That’s the good news. There’s also bad news. The work is hard, extensive, and slow. It took decades to create our current landscape, and it will be decades to restore it. We will see progress over the course of our lifetimes — but probably only fairly modest progress. The work that needs to be done is also controversial, with opposition from both those who benefit from an exploitable landscape and those who, operating under dated ideologies of “let nature run its course,” see the work that needs to be done as immoral.</p>
<p>What can we do? Pick a patch and get to work. Don’t forget about the forest, but focusing your attention on one stand of trees will let you make a visible difference on a human timescale. And work in solidarity. The work needs different skills, capacities, and resources. No one person can do everything that needs to be done, and we all can contribute in our own way.</p>
<p>Above all, remember that a better world is possible, and we are the ones we’ve been waiting for.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-11-08-fire-ecology.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Writing a draft is sketching, not vomiting</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-10-04-writing-sketching.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Yesterday our Environmental Philosophy class had an interesting discussion about writing first drafts. Several of the students used a vomiting metaphor to describe this stage of the writing process, as in, vomiting all your ideas out onto the page. The essays we read to start this conversation didn’t use this metaphor, but multiple small groups independently suggested it.</p>
<p>I think the vomiting metaphor is meant to express the sense that writing a first draft is messy and thorough. A first draft doesn’t need to tightly follow an assignment structure or other formal requirements; it’ll always have a mix of good ideas and bad ones; and it’s okay if the grammar and word choice are awkward or idiosyncratic. You also want all of your potential ideas out on paper, where you can take a closer look at them, and really figure out which ones are better or worse.</p>
<p>So, don’t hold back, let it all just go everywhere, and clean things up afterwards.</p>
<p>The thing is, vomiting is really unpleasant. No one enjoys vomiting, even if it sometimes brings some relief to an upset stomach. It’s also involuntary and uncontrolled, rather than deliberate and skillful. You don’t need to practice vomiting to get good at it. (And the idea of being <em>good at vomiting</em> is also pretty weird itself!)</p>
<p>Talking with the students, I realized that <em>sketching</em> is a much better metaphor for my process of writing a first draft. As in, sketching a drawing or painting.</p>
<p>As in the vomiting metaphor, a sketch doesn’t tightly follow formal requirements. Indeed, the point of a sketch is often to figure out the general form and composition of the image. Sketching is done quickly and lightly, with lots of little changes along the way as you figure out what does and doesn’t work. A sketch might contain variations on an element, to identify which representations of that element are better and worse.</p>
<p>But, unlike vomiting, sketching is a deliberate and skillful activity. It requires practice, and can involve different techniques of varying complexity and effort. It’s also often pleasant and stimulating.</p>
<p>Consider this blog post. I’m taking time out of a very busy day to write it, because after class I just couldn’t get “vomiting vs.&nbsp;sketching” out of my head. I was too excited to find a way to explain this idea to other people. And, even more importantly, I needed to work out <em>for myself</em> exactly what I meant, why I thought sketching was a better metaphor for my writing process. As I write, I’m coming up with even more ideas, and what was meant to be about 300 words long is now creeping towards 500 (and beyond). When I vomit, I’m not excited to keep vomiting even more.</p>
<p>When we make a sketch — for a drawing, a painting, or a photograph or video shot — we start with a vague, poorly-defined concept or reaction to a scene. There’s <em>something</em> here we want to express, but usually we’re not really sure what that <em>something</em> is. Sketching is the process whereby we consider different elements, seen in different ways, arranged in different compositions, hopefully working our way towards that original <em>something</em>. When we find it — when the sketch is successful — it has a feeling of both creation and discovery. Creation because it’s a thing we’ve created, it’s emerged out of us and now exists in the world. But also discovery, because at the start we didn’t know exactly what that <em>something</em> was. The sketch reveals that <em>something</em> to us, enabling us to share it with others but also understand it better ourselves.</p>
<p>For me, philosophy also starts with that <em>something</em>, a vague reaction to the ideas of another. Sometimes it’s vague agreement; sometimes it’s vague disagreement. Most often it’s that I don’t quite see things the way the other person does, and the <em>something</em> is the combination of our agreements and disagreements. Writing — sketching — is the process by which I try to discover and explain that vague reaction.</p>
<p>This is what philosophers mean when we say that writing is our research method.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-10-04-writing-sketching.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why aren’t Trump supporters worried about the Seal Team 6 Scenario? (Rejected from r/AskTrumpSupporters)</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-07-14-seal-team-6.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This was originally written as a Reddit post on July 5, about a week after the Trump v. US decision.</em></p>
<p>The “Seal Team 6 Scenario” is where the President orders an assassination of a political rival. Arguably, under the <em>Trump v. US</em> decision, this would fall within the President’s “core powers” as Commander in Chief, and so would be immune from any criminal prosecution. A lot of Trump opponents are worried about this scenario, but TS [Trump supporters] don’t seem to be. In the <em>Trump</em> decision, the majority just dismissed it as “hyperbolic,” without actually refuting the argument.</p>
<p>But it seems to me like TS <em>should</em> be worried about this kind of scenario:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>A lot of TS believe that Democratic political leaders are/have been/will be willing to use antidemocratic/tyrannical/authoritarian measures to secure power.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Trump v. US</em> allows things like political assassination.</p></li>
<li><p>We have a Democratic president now, it’s a live possibility that we’ll have a Democratic president a year from now, and we’ll almost certainly have a Democratic president sooner or later.</p></li>
<li><p>So, from the perspective of a lot of TS, there’s a live possibility that, sooner or later, a Democratic political leader will use political assassination to secure power.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>“Live possibility” doesn’t mean it’s especially likely, just that it’s something that might foreseeably happen. Like, if Biden only has a 25% chance of legitimately winning the election (1:3 odds), he’s definitely not favored. But his chances are way better than rolling snake eyes on a pair of dice (1:35 odds, about 3% chance) or drawing two pair in poker (about 5% chance).</p>
<p>So if you’re not worried about the Seal Team 6 Scenario, where’s the misstep in my argument 1-4?</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-07-14-seal-team-6.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Were you aware that Democrats do not want to undermine democracy? (Rejected from r/AskTrumpSupporters)</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-07-14-undermine-democracy.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I’m somewhat active on the subreddit <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskTrumpSupporters/">r/AskTrumpSupporters</a>. The board is intended to be a place where Trump supporters and critics can talk about the differences across their views. I don’t think it’s very successful at this, due to a combination of high rates of trolling by supporters and critics flooding supporters’ replies.</p>
<p>But I still sometimes try to post questions there. These are usually rejected. I’m not sure why, since I <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskTrumpSupporters/wiki/index/#wiki_posting_guidelines">try to follow the guidelines</a> and the mods don’t give any explanation for rejections. Since these posts take some effort, I thought I’d put them up here.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><em>This post was originally written March 17, 2024</em></p>
<p>Were you aware that Democrats do not want to undermine democracy?</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-023-01594-w">this political science study</a>, they asked both Democrats and Republicans whether they would support take steps to undermine democracy if it hurt the other party, and then what they think members of the other party would support. They specifically asked about:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>reducing the number of voting stations</li>
<li>banning rallies</li>
<li>ignoring controversial court rulings</li>
<li>freezing the social media accounts of journalists</li>
<li>changing laws to make it easier for one’s own side to get elected</li>
<li>using violence to block laws</li>
<li>reinterpreting the Constitution to block policies</li>
</ol>
<p>For both Democrats and Republicans, the most common response to most items was that they would “never” support it, and 60-80% said they would “never or probably not” support it.*</p>
<p>So neither party supports undermining democracy. But each party thinks the other would support these things. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-023-01594-w/figures/1">Figure 1</a> shows how dramatically we misunderstand each other. The authors argue that:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>This provides would-be authoritarians with a powerful weapon against democracy. They use propaganda to convince their supporters that the other side is undermining democracy. As their supporters come to believe that the other side is defecting, they are more willing to tolerate their leaders’ antidemocratic actions, which are seen as merely levelling the playing field now tilted against them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What do you think of this?</p>
<p>* In <a href="https://static-content.springer.com/esm/art%3A10.1038%2Fs41562-023-01594-w/MediaObjects/41562_2023_1594_MOESM1_ESM.pdf">the supplementary info</a>, you can see the breakdown of responses for individual items on pages 24-25. For Democrats, for two items “probably not” was more common than “never”: banning rallies by the far right and freezing the social media accounts of journalists. Except for banning rallies, no more than 30% of Democrats said they would “probably” or “definitely” support taking the step. For Republicans, “probably not” was more common than “never” for banning rallies by the far left and ignoring controversial court rulings.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-07-14-undermine-democracy.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Defusing the Democracy Defense: Scientists as Epistemic Representatives</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-04-05-dewey-center-talk.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I gave a talk at the Center for Dewey Studies in Carbondale on April 4. Slides are <a href="https://epistemic-rep.netlify.app/">here</a>, the recording is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1tKTnaKNt0Y">here</a>, and the abstract is below.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For decades, traditional notions of objectivity and ideals of politically neutral, “value-free” science have been challenged by the history, philosophy, and social studies of science. For most scholars in these fields, science is unavoidably “shot through with values,” and value-laden decisions appear throughout the “nooks and crannies” of everyday scientific research. But some have pushed back, arguing that accepting value-ladenness would allow scientists to undemocratically impose their values on everyone else. This is the “democracy defense” of value-free science.</p>
<p>One line of response to the democracy defense appeals to ideas of deliberative democracy, imagining increased public participation in science-based policymaking. But deliberative democratic approaches have difficulty reaching into the “nooks and crannies” of scientific research itself, where it would be impractical for scientists to consult with the public.</p>
<p>In this talk, I consider whether the theory of political representation might be useful for thinking about when and how the judgment of a select few can democratically represent the general public. In other words, can we think of scientists as epistemic representatives, more or less the way politicians serve as political representatives? I suggest that recent work in political theory, on informal representation and systems of democratic representation, are promising for such an approach.</p>
</blockquote>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2024-04-05-dewey-center-talk.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Epistemic interdependence or epistemic hierarchy</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-11-12-epistemic-interdependence.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Given my intests in public scientific controversies and the politics of expertise, it might be a little surprising that I don’t really find much of interest in the social epistemology literature on expertise. I was reading a social epistemology paper yesterday that helped me articulate one reason for this: how we frame the need for expertise.</p>
<hr>
<p>I frame this need in terms of <em>epistemic interdependence</em>. For example, when we started a unit on appeal to authority <a href="https://fairy-shrimp.netlify.app/09-expertise.html#epistemic-interdependence">in Critical Reasoning this semester</a>, I first estimated that</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>it would take you about 17 million minutes, or about 287,000 hours, to read the entirety of Wikipedia. Working 24/7/365.26, that’s a bit less than 33 years. Working full time (40 hours/week for 50 weeks per year) it’s 143 years.</p>
<p>And that’s just for the brief, nontechnical summary of collective human knowledge in a single language.</p>
<p>Humans depend on each other in a variety of ways. We need others to take care of us when we’re young, sick, and elderly. We distribute the work of making useful things across different job categories and industries, along with the work of getting useful things from the places they’re made to the places where they’re used. We’re also <strong>epistemically interdependent</strong>: we rely on each other to produce and circulate knowledge about the world.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Basically, there’s so much to know that one person can’t do it all. We need other people to know things on our behalf. Experts are the people to whom we entrust this knowing. I go on to introduce <a href="https://fairy-shrimp.netlify.app/09-expertise.html#two-sources-of-expertise">two sources of expertise</a>, formal education or training and lived experience. Taking into account lived experience, most people have expertise in something, though often the scope is very local. I give the example of one of the nieces, who has expertise in the social groups of her high school. One student suggested that her mom has expertise in the mystery novels written by her favorite author. I also talk about ACT-UP and environmental justice movements, as examples of marginalized people — generally completely lacking formal training in science — who became scientific experts.</p>
<p>The examples of ACT-UP and environmental justice also motivate a key distinction in feminist accounts of trustworthiness <span class="citation" data-cites="AlmassiRelationallyResponsiveExpert2022">(Almassi 2022)</span>, between <a href="https://fairy-shrimp.netlify.app/09-expertise.html#act-up-and-unresponsive-experts">competence and responsiveness</a>: during the HIV-AIDS crisis, public health authorities were entirely competent credentialed experts, but were unresponsive to the concerns of ACT-UP and consequently were not trustworthy. We can same basically the same thing about EPA and environmental justice communities.</p>
<p>In this framing, I’m assuming that most people have more or less the same potential or “innate capacity” for expertise. The difference between credentialed experts and groups like ACT-UP is primarily the accident of privilege vs.&nbsp;marginalization, and even marginalized groups can successfully challenge credentialed experts in highly technical domains — though this probably requires a lot of organization and hard work, and will be of very restricted scope.<sup>1</sup></p>
<hr>
<p>By contrast, here’s how <span class="citation" data-cites="GrundmannFacingEpistemicAuthorities2021">Grundmann (2021)</span> frames expertise:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Epistemic abilities are unequally distributed in society. Not everyone has the same cognitive competences. Some people stand out by being much more reliable than average …. Epistemic superiority is the product of two independent factors: the available body of evidence and one’s reasoning competences …. Some people have a more reliable judgment than others because they are more clever in drawing rational inferences from the shared body of evidence. This is, e.g., the case when Sherlock Holmes outperforms Watson in his judgments about who was the murderer. <span class="citation" data-cites="GrundmannFacingEpistemicAuthorities2021">(Grundmann 2021, 138–39)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Call this framing <em>epistemic hierarchy</em>. Given a set of evidence, this framing suggests that we can rank people in order of their “cognitive competences,” and the experts are the ones with the best/most/greatest cognitive competence. This hierarchical framing is reinforced by referring to non-experts as “laypeople,” evoking the formal hierarchy of the Catholic church.</p>
<p>Grundmann does qualify this hierarchical framing, noting that “epistemic superiority … is always relative to a domain of expertise” (ibid.), and of course often some people will have access to more or better evidence than others. But these qualifications are often quietly dropped or bracketed. Grundmann defines “epistemic authority” with respect to domain D; but then refers to “superior reasoning competences” simpliciter, that is, not <em>domain-specific</em> reasoning competences. The definition also requires that the candidate authority “has very likely considered all of [the trustor’s] relevant evidence” (ibid.) By dropping these qualifications — and using Sherlock Holmes as the paradigm of an expert — this framing tends to suggest that expertise is primarily a matter of cognitive competence. And, further, seeing cognitive competence as “unequally distributed in society” suggests to me that cognitive competence — and thus expertise — is primarily a matter of innate “general intelligence.”<sup>2</sup><sup>3</sup> In short, with this framing, it seems to me quite easy to slide from domain-specific and dynamic comparisons that might not form a total order (A has better evidence, B has better domain-specific reasoning) to a domain-general epistemic hierarchy based on an innate ability.</p>
<p>(I want to stress that the implicatures and slides I see in the last paragraph aren’t logical entailments. I’m not claiming that, if you adopt this framing, you’re thereby committed to some sort of epistemic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_chain_of_being">scala natura</a>. My point is more that this framing coheres with the idea of a natural hierarchy based on intelligence, and can easily be read as either assuming or justifying such a hierarchy.)</p>
<p>Working with the epistemic hierarchy framing, <span class="citation" data-cites="GrundmannFacingEpistemicAuthorities2021">Grundmann (2021)</span> goes on to argue for the “Preemption View” of “layperson”-expert relations:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>When we discover that an epistemic authority believes that p, we should not make any more use of our own reasoning about p as evidence for or against p.&nbsp;The use of our own reasoning concerning p is to be bracketed. <span class="citation" data-cites="GrundmannFacingEpistemicAuthorities2021">(Grundmann 2021, 140)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In short, the “layperson” should defer to the expert’s judgment, and in particular should not challenge the expert’s reasoning, because of the expert’s superior cognitive capabilities (within the domain, and given that the expert has a superset of the layperson’s evidence). I didn’t read the rest of the paper carefully, but from here <span class="citation" data-cites="GrundmannFacingEpistemicAuthorities2021">Grundmann (2021)</span> seems to argue that a failure to follow the Preemption View explains why we have a problem with conspiracy theories and rampant misinformation.</p>
<p>It’s hard to read the cases of ACT-UP, environmental justice, or feminist history of science into this analysis. I suppose one could say that the marginalized groups in each case had access to evidence that the purported authority did not, or the purported authorities neglected relevant evidence, or something like this; and thus they were not actually authorities. But then the whole analysis of <span class="citation" data-cites="GrundmannFacingEpistemicAuthorities2021">Grundmann (2021)</span> is irrelevant, in a strictly logical sense: an early premise in the big argument (145) is false and so we get no particular guidance on these kinds of cases.</p>
<hr>
<p>One additional contrast between these framings seems noteworthy. Epistemic interdependence lends itself to posing the “question of expertise” in terms of trust: who should I trust (or) who is trustworthy? Starting by asking about trust, and reflecting on trust and vulnerability — in the footsteps of feminist philosophers — can lead us to a conception of trustworthiness that requires responsiveness along with (epistemic) competence. Expertise is a power relation, and the people with power (experts) can cause great harm when they abuse this power or use it to perpetrate injustice.</p>
<p>The epistemic hierarchy framing seems to understand the “question of expertise” in terms of the doxastic attitude that an (abstracted) agent should take towards an (abstracted) proposition: should S believe that p? Specifically, should S believe that p on the grounds that this other person A says so? Insofar as the ultimate virtue of belief is truth, the ultimate virtue of an expert is whether their claims are more likely to be true. Unless they can be reframed in terms of truth,<sup>4</sup> questions of power, vulnerability, and justice are lost in the brilliant glare cast by truth.</p>
<p>So this is one major reason why so much of the social epistemology literature leaves me cold. Not only does it deploy a rival framing of the question of expertise — with some implicatures that I find highly disagreeable — but, within this framing, it’s difficult to explore the kinds of cases that motivate me and ask the kinds of questions that I want to ask.</p>





<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-AlmassiRelationallyResponsiveExpert2022" class="csl-entry">
Almassi, Ben. 2022. <span>“Relationally Responsive Expert Trustworthiness.”</span> <em>Social Epistemology</em> 36 (5): 576–85. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/02691728.2022.2103475">https://doi.org/10.1080/02691728.2022.2103475</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-GrundmannFacingEpistemicAuthorities2021" class="csl-entry">
Grundmann, Thomas. 2021. <span>“Facing Epistemic Authorities: Where Democratic Ideals and Critical Thinking Mislead Cognition.”</span> In <em>The Epistemology of Fake News</em>, edited by Sven Bernecker, Amy K. Flowerree, and Thomas Grundmann, 0. Oxford University Press. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/oso/9780198863977.003.0007">https://doi.org/10.1093/oso/9780198863977.003.0007</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This point didn’t come up in class, but we could also say that queer communities often had expertise in <em>what it’s like to life with HIV-AIDS</em> that public health authorities generally lacked. The epistemic interdependence runs both ways; no party has uniformly better knowledge than any other party.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>A dedicated Holmes fan might object that Holmes’ abilities were much more dependent on domain-specific reasoning and a vast mental storehouse of esoteric evidence than “innate general intelligence.” This is correct; I vaguely recall a scene in which Watson is surprised that Holmes doesn’t know some commonplace fact (maybe Holmes doesn’t recognize the name of a popular opera singer?), and Holmes explains that he is intentionally ignorant of basically everything that’s not relevant to solving crime. But I would argue that Doyle also portrays Holmes’ capabilities as a matter of innate general intelligence — for example, his brother Mycroft has the same innate genius, just applied to national security and espionage — and the <em>popular</em> understanding of Holmes emphasizes his supposed innate general intelligence.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I’ve also spent a lot of time the last 2-1/2 year working on a project on race science, which might make me oversensitive to the possibility that ideas of innate general intelligence are waiting just offstage.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>I think the “epistemic injustice” literature is often trying to do this, which is probably why I don’t find that literature particularly engaging either.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-11-12-epistemic-interdependence.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Fact checking ChatGPT: An activity for Critical Thinking</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-11-10-ChatGPT.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week I did a “fact checking ChatGPT” activity with my Critical Thinking class. It has some distinct aims from other ChatGPT activities I’ve seen, and seemed to work well, so I thought I’d write it up real quick.</p>
<p>I’ve seen lots of examples of classroom activities that explore the limitations (and strengths) of ChatGPT as a writer. Some of my students mentioned they or their friends had done things like this. For this activity, I decided to focus instead on ChatGPT as a source of information. We’ve just spent three weeks learning how to evaluate other sources: <a href="https://fairy-shrimp.netlify.app/09-expertise.html">a unit on appeals to authority</a> based on <a href="https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-09-25-teaching-expertise.html">feminist work on epistemic trustworthiness</a>, and then <a href="https://fairy-shrimp.netlify.app/11-SIFT-1.html">a unit on fact checking (social) media using the SIFT method</a>.</p>
<p>To prepare for the activity, I asked students to create an OpenAI account if they didn’t already have one, and bring their laptops to class if they don’t usually do so. I also told them to read Ted Chiang’s <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/tech/annals-of-technology/chatgpt-is-a-blurry-jpeg-of-the-web">essay</a> “ChatGPT is a Blurry JPEG of the Web,” and set up the Google Sheet that’s linked below.</p>
<p>Then, in class, I gave students these instructions for the activity:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Prompt ChatGPT to write a short paper on a topic that includes citations and a bibliography: &gt; Hi ChatGPT. Can you write a short paper on the rise of college debt, including a bibliography with five recent academic citations?</p></li>
<li><p>For each bibliography entry, use search tools to try to determine whether the item actually exists.</p>
<ul>
<li>Does the author list match what ChatGPT said?</li>
<li>Was it published in the place ChatGPT said it was published?</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Record your findings on this Google Sheet: <a href="https://tinyurl.com/2xdcz7mo">tinyurl.com/2xdcz7mo</a></p></li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://dhicks.github.io/img/2023-11-10-ChatGPT-spreadsheet.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The first few rows of the spreadsheet</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The spreadsheet was set to “anyone can edit.” I filled in the first few rows myself as an example, using the citations from the essay ChatGPT generated in response to my college debt prompt. Columns C, E, and F (does the item exist, does the author list match, does the publication info match) use data validation rules, restricting the possible values. This makes it simple to set up the pivot table in the “exists?” sheet, which we use in the debrief/reflection phase.</p>
<p>The prompt needs to request citations and a bibliography explicitly; otherwise ChatGPT doesn’t include them. This might be different if you’re using something like Microsoft Bing Chat.</p>
<p>After walking through the instructions abstractly, I gave a short demonstration by repeating the work I’d done with the first couple of rows. This included a quick reminder of Google Scholar, which a student had mentioned a few weeks earlier when we were discussing expertise.</p>
<p>Students spent about 40 minutes working on this activity, mostly in pairs or individually. I said explicitly that I wanted to get as large a sample of bib items as possible, and so didn’t want them to work in their table-groups (5-8 students). It was a nice, chill, student-oriented class session: I just wandered around, answering questions, helping with the rare tricky case, and chatting with students.</p>
<p>To close out the activity, I spent 15 minutes on a whole-class discussion of three questions:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>How frequently did ChatGPT manufacture citations?</p></li>
<li><p>How does this relate to Chiang’s essay, “ChatGPT Is a Blurry JPEG of the Web”?</p></li>
<li><p>What implications does this have for using LLMs like ChatGPT</p>
<ul>
<li>To write papers?</li>
<li>As information sources (Google Bard, Microsoft Bing Chat)?</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>Question 1 was easy to answer with the pivot table. In our case, ChatGPT manufactured 38% of citations (counting only the ones that do not exist at all) or 58% (including the ones that exist but have metadata errors). A few students said this is what they expected to see — based on doing some similar experiments on their own — but I and other students expected the rate of manufactured citations to be somewhat higher.</p>
<p>Not many of the students had really digested Chiang’s essay, so this turned into an impromptu lecture. We’re covering argument by analogy next week, so I’ll probably use Chiang’s analogy as a recurrent example.</p>
<p>Students were pretty thoughtful about the implications. We talked about how faculty are experts, and can instantly recognize manufactured citations in our areas of expertise. Students were a little uncertain about how to regard the citations that actually existed. Some felt these were reliable, but others made the inference that you’d have to actually go and read the paper itself to figure out whether it made the claims ChatGPT was attributing to it. In their one-minute papers, lots of students indicated that they no longer trust ChatGPT as a source of information.</p>
<p>All together, this activity went really well: students were very engaged, and came away with a healthy skepticism of LLMs. Next time, I might make the spreadsheet-filling itself homework rather than an in-class activity. Specifically, I might devote the last 15-20 minutes of the previous session to getting student started on filling in the spreadsheet, then have them complete it (for two different prompts) before the next session. Then, in “the ChatGPT session proper,” we’d start with 10 minutes or so on any tricky references, and have about an hour for the reflective discussion. This would give us lots of time to unpack Chinag’s essay and relate it to the results of the fact check.</p>
<hr>
<p>Coincidentally, this morning <em>Nature</em> published a very nice Perspective piece that proposes two non-anthropomorphic conceptual frameworks for thinking about the behavior of LLMs <span class="citation" data-cites="ShanahanRolePlayLarge2023">(Shanahan, McDonell, and Reynolds 2023)</span>. Their second framework is a bit technical for the typical first-year undergrad. But the first framework is very accessible: LLMs as role-playing, or specifically as actors in an improv show.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>If the model has generalized well from the training data, the most plausible continuation [of the prompt text] will be a response to the user that conforms to the expectations we would have of someone who fits the description in the preamble. In other words, the dialogue agent will do its best to role-play the character of a dialogue agent as portrayed in the dialogue prompt ….</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>What sorts of roles might the agent begin to take on? This is determined in part, of course, by the tone and subject matter of the ongoing conversation. But it is also determined, in large part, by the panoply of characters that feature in the training set, which encompasses a multitude of novels, screenplays, biographies, interview transcripts, newspaper articles and so on. In effect, the training set provisions the language model with a vast repertoire of archetypes and a rich trove of narrative structure on which to draw as it ‘chooses’ how to continue a conversation, refining the role it is playing as it goes, while staying in character.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Like an experienced improv actor, a LLM is able to adopt the distinctive behaviors of the role they’re playing, making the role very convincing. But — when playing the role of an expert — this doesn’t come with the competence required for actual expertise. An actor can play an expert in starship engineering, for example, saying the kinds of things we’d expect starship engineers to say (based on decades of fiction featuring starship engineer characters), without any actual knowledge of starship engineering. Similarly, a LLM can convincingly say the kinds of things that we expect student loan experts to say — including producing the kinds of citations that student loan experts use in their papers — without any actual knowledge of student loans.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-ShanahanRolePlayLarge2023" class="csl-entry">
Shanahan, Murray, Kyle McDonell, and Laria Reynolds. 2023. <span>“Role Play with Large Language Models.”</span> <em>Nature</em>, November, 1–6. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06647-8">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06647-8</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-11-10-ChatGPT.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Teaching ethics of expertise in Critical Thinking</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-09-25-teaching-expertise.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m teaching expertise and appeals to authority in Critical Thinking about a month, and start to wrestle yet again with how to approach this.</p>
<p>The textbook I use — like pretty much all of them? — takes the “believe the impartial sources who have the right credentials” approach. Completely out of touch with five decades of feminist philosophy and STS.</p>
<p>I want to start by talking about multiple sources of expertise (credentials, but also lived experience), then Baier’s conception of trust and subsequent work on the ethics+epistemology of trust. Using Baier’s conception suggests two relatively clear criteria for a trustworthy expert:</p>
<dl>
<dt>competence</dt>
<dd>
On the topic in question, the expert is likely to have true beliefs.
</dd>
<dt>responsiveness</dt>
<dd>
“[T]hey have encapsulated my interests: the trusted party pursues or protects particular interests, at least in part, because they are the trusted party’s interests …. the expectation that the [expert] will be directly and favorably moved by the thought that we are counting on her” <span class="citation" data-cites="AlmassiRelationallyResponsiveExpert2022">(Almassi 2022, 578)</span>
</dd>
</dl>
<p>From here we can talk about why different groups of people can reasonably assess the trustworthiness of experts differently. And <span class="citation" data-cites="AlmassiRelationallyResponsiveExpert2022">Almassi (2022)</span> has a really nice argument that “owning the libs” — communicating that one is actively hostile towards an outgroup — isn’t actually evidence that they’re interested in promoting the ingroup’s interests, and thus does not make them more trustworthy for members of the ingroup. Which will nicely fit into our discussion, over the subsequent two weeks, of the SIFT method for assessing online information sources and then whether ChatGPT is trustworthy (spoiler alert: it is not).</p>
<p>So class time looks good. Where I’m feeling uncertainty is in assessment.</p>
<p>In this class, the discrete course units are assessed using a weekly quiz. The quiz has a simple format: students are given an argument as a paragraph of prose, and then have to answer a series of short response questions that walk them through analyzing the argument. The short response questions are explicitly tied to “rules” that the textbook gives for assessing that type of argument. In theory, this direct line between assessments and course content will help students study. For example, last year’s course used this question to get at competence:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>What is the source’s area of expertise? Is this credentialed or experiential expertise? (Rule 14)</p>
<p>Expectations: 1 sentence characterizing area and source of expertise.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A typical prompt/argument to analyze for this unit goes like this:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Massimiliano Vasile, an aerospace engineer at the University of Glasgow, spent two years comparing nine different technologies that could be used if an asteroid were on a collision course with Earth. Dr.&nbsp;Vasile’s study revealed that it would be a bad idea to blow up an incoming asteroid with nuclear weapons. Thus, blowing up Earth-bound asteroids with nuclear weapons is a bad idea. <span class="small">(Adapted from: Lia Miller, “The Best Way to Deflect an Asteroid,” New York Times Magazine, December 9, 2007, &lt;http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/09/magazine/ 09_5_asteroid.html&gt;)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Prompts like this contain no useful information for assessing responsiveness. Examples of appeal to expertise like this “seem to treat our communities of inquirers rather generically …. experts’ particular relationship to us … is elided, treated as irrelevant to the question at hand” <span class="citation" data-cites="AlmassiRelationallyResponsiveExpert2022">(Almassi 2022, 578)</span>.</p>
<p>Some prompts do give negative information, indications that the expert is not responsive to our interests, in the form of indicators that the source has a financial conflict of interest, “four out of five doctors smoke Camels.” That’s something, but I don’t want to reduce responsiveness to a question about conflicts of interest.</p>
<p>I need 7 of these prompts (there’s a new quiz each week, so students can re-take them until they pass). Scrapping them all — or almost all of them — and writing whole new ones would be a lot of work. If I have to go actively looking, it can take 60-90 minutes to find a good example — usually from a piece of science journalism — and distill it into a single, undergrad-accessible paragraph.</p>
<p>My dilemma is this: Stick with an inadequate approach to expertise, or put in an extra 7-10 hours of work to rewrite the quizzes?</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-AlmassiRelationallyResponsiveExpert2022" class="csl-entry">
Almassi, Ben. 2022. <span>“Relationally Responsive Expert Trustworthiness.”</span> <em>Social Epistemology</em> 36 (5): 576–85. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/02691728.2022.2103475">https://doi.org/10.1080/02691728.2022.2103475</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-09-25-teaching-expertise.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Do scientists have power? Does science?</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-09-20-power.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I recently read (most of) <span class="citation" data-cites="LukesPowerRadicalView2005">Lukes (2005)</span>. Lukes offers an influential account of (political) power, and I wanted to see if it would be useful for answering a question that came up in a discussion with (IIRC) Heather Douglas and Matt Brown quite a while ago: Do scientists have power?</p>
<p>Lukes identifies three “faces” of power. Unless I missed something, his definitions for these “faces” aren’t very clear; they’re often demonstrative or negative. And he doesn’t label them. So here’s a quick attempt at labeled, positive definitions:</p>
<dl>
<dt>coercive</dt>
<dd>
This is what we usually think of as political power: comply or you will be harmed.
</dd>
<dt>prioritizing</dt>
<dd>
Influencing whose interests have priority, are seen as important and should be protected or promoted. Lukes talks about this with respect to agenda-setting, as in whose complaints show up on the agenda.
</dd>
<dt>ideological</dt>
<dd>
Influencing how interests are recognized and understood. In terms of Brown’s Deweyan model of inquiry <span class="citation" data-cites="BrownScienceMoralImagination2020">(Brown 2020)</span>, ideological power shapes not only how a problem is framed, but potentially also <em>whether a situation is experienced as indeterminate or problematic in the first place</em>.
</dd>
</dl>
<hr>
<p>Given these definitions, do scientists have power?</p>
<p>As posed, the question is ambiguous, between individualistic and corporate readings of “scientists.” Let’s use “scientists” for the individualistic reading (do certain particular scientists have power?) and “science” for the corporate reading (does science as an institution have power?)</p>
<p>Individual scientists basically never have coercive power. Even when a scientist, qua scientist, works for the state, the role of scientist doesn’t come with law enforcement powers or some other entitlement to coercive power.</p>
<p>On the other hand, individual scientists can have prioritizing and ideological power. In the risk assessment framework, the first phase is “problem formulation and scoping,” which is supposed to be on the “politics” side of the science/politics dichotomy. But typically risk assessment is initiated in response to scientific findings — findings made, communicated, and taken up by certain particular scientists, qua scientists — that indicate a problem and its potential severity.</p>
<p>In these kinds of cases, individual scientists generally won’t have <em>exclusive</em> prioritizing and ideological power. At EPA or other regulatory agencies, certain particular political appointees and “regulatory” (as opposed to “scientific”) staff will also exercise these forms of power.</p>
<p>And, outside of regulatory agencies, individual scientists often do not have any more prioritizing or ideological power than any other member of the public. Well-connected faculty at prestigious universities might be able to exercise this kind of power. (I’m thinking of Scott Atlas, a Hoover Institution fellow who was on Trump’s Coronavirus Task Force, or the psychologist Arthur Jensen, who was a professor at Berkeley and became well-know to the public for his race science views.)</p>
<p>So, academic scientists, <em>as individuals</em>, generally don’t have much of any of the three forms of power.</p>
<hr>
<p>Turn now to science in the corporate sense, and specifically institutions that are taken to speak on behalf of science: EPA, IPCC, the National Academies, AAAS.</p>
<p>Regulatory agencies, like EPA, do have coercive power. Though the prioritizing and ideological power of regulated industries means that EPA doesn’t exercise that coercive power as much as I would like. Still, insofar as EPA is a representative of “science,” and does exercise coercive power, we can understand this as science exercising (and therefore having) coercive power.</p>
<p>The other science institutions that I listed above don’t have coercive power. But they do have substantial prioritizing and ideological power. The National Academies basically made up the risk assessment framework, which is a fundamental component of how environmental health threats are understood and prioritized. Indeed, even the category label “environmental health threats” adopts some assumptions of the risk assessment framework. Opponents of genetically modified foods have a number of concerns that aren’t related to health and safety <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksGMOsNonhealthIssues2016">(Hicks and Millstein 2016)</span> and are therefore systematically ignored by regulatory agencies <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksGeneticallyModifiedCrops2017">(Hicks 2017)</span>.</p>
<p>Using Lukes’ terminology, a whole strain of STS is devoted to studying the prioritizing and ideological power of scientism: on the assumption that only “scientific” evidence counts as evidence, claims that a situation is problematic, is sufficiently severe and warrants action, and that the key cause of the problem is such-and-such, all need to be justified by “scientific” evidence <span class="citation" data-cites="WynneSheepfarmingChernobylCase1989 EpsteinImpureScience1996 FrickelUndoneScienceCharting2010 KleinmanHoneyBeesThreat2013 SuryanarayananVanishingBeesScience2016">(Wynne 1989; Epstein 1996; Frickel et al. 2010; Kleinman and Suryanarayanan 2013; Suryanarayanan and Kleinman 2016)</span>.</p>
<p>Scientism has this power because it serves the interests of multiple groups. Most obviously it bolsters the status of scientists. It was taken up by regulatory agencies as a strategy to maintain legitimacy in the face of opposition from regulated industries <span class="citation" data-cites="JasanoffFifthBranchScience1998">(Jasanoff 1998)</span>. But, at the same time, regulated industries have used it to dismiss criticism and block or delay regulation <span class="citation" data-cites="MichaelsDoubtTheirProduct2008">(Michaels 2008)</span>.</p>
<hr>
<p>If we think of political power only in coercive terms, then it’s difficult to come up with examples of the political power of science beyond agencies like EPA. <span class="citation" data-cites="LukesPowerRadicalView2005">Lukes (2005)</span> is explicitly challenging a parallel situation in mid-century political science: a line of research that studied “power,” but understood it only as coercive power, and generally came to the conclusion that there are not significant concentrations of power in American politics. He identified prioritization power in some previous research, and proposed ideological power as all but completely overlooked by empirical political scientists.</p>
<p>When we follow Lukes in thinking of power in terms of shaping the agenda and framing the recognition and understanding of problematic situations, then it’s much easier to articulate the political power of science. Science has power not because it can threaten you with imprisonment, but rather because problems that aren’t articulated and diagnosed “scientifically” are systematically ignored.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-BrownScienceMoralImagination2020" class="csl-entry">
Brown, Matthew. 2020. <em>Science and Moral Imagination: A New Ideal for Values in Science</em>. University of Pittsburgh Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-EpsteinImpureScience1996" class="csl-entry">
Epstein, Steven. 1996. <em>Impure Science</em>. AIDS, Activism, and the Politics of Knowledge. Berkeley, Los Angeles, and Oxford: University of California Press. <a href="http://books.google.ca/books?id=kZOso0FMsrMC&amp;pg=PA39&amp;dq=intitle:Impure+Science+inauthor:epstein&amp;hl=&amp;cd=1&amp;source=gbs_api">http://books.google.ca/books?id=kZOso0FMsrMC&amp;pg=PA39&amp;dq=intitle:Impure+Science+inauthor:epstein&amp;hl=&amp;cd=1&amp;source=gbs_api</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-FrickelUndoneScienceCharting2010" class="csl-entry">
Frickel, S., S. Gibbon, J. Howard, J. Kempner, G. Ottinger, and D. J. Hess. 2010. <span>“Undone Science: Charting Social Movement and Civil Society Challenges to Research Agenda Setting.”</span> <em>Science, Technology &amp; Human Values</em> 35 (4): 444–73. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243909345836">https://doi.org/10.1177/0162243909345836</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksGeneticallyModifiedCrops2017" class="csl-entry">
Hicks, Daniel J. 2017. <span>“Genetically Modified Crops, Inclusion, and Democracy.”</span> <em>Perspectives on Science</em> 25 (4): 488–520. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/POSC_a_00251">https://doi.org/10.1162/POSC_a_00251</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksGMOsNonhealthIssues2016" class="csl-entry">
Hicks, Daniel J., and Roberta L. Millstein. 2016. <span>“GMOs: Non-Health Issues.”</span> In <em>Encyclopedia of Food and Agricultural Ethics</em>, edited by Paul B. Thompson and David M. Kaplan, 1–11. Springer Netherlands. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-6167-4_545-1">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-6167-4_545-1</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-JasanoffFifthBranchScience1998" class="csl-entry">
Jasanoff, Sheila. 1998. <em>The Fifth Branch: Science Advisers as Policymakers</em>. Harvard University Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-KleinmanHoneyBeesThreat2013" class="csl-entry">
Kleinman, Daniel Lee, and Sainath Suryanarayanan. 2013. <span>“Honey Bees Under Threat: A Political Pollinator Crisis.”</span> <em>The Guardian</em>, May 8, 2013, sec. Science. <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/science/political-science/2013/may/08/honey-bees-threat-political-pollinator-crisis">http://www.theguardian.com/science/political-science/2013/may/08/honey-bees-threat-political-pollinator-crisis</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LukesPowerRadicalView2005" class="csl-entry">
Lukes, Steven. 2005. <em>Power: A Radical View, Second Edition</em>. Palgrave Macmillan.
</div>
<div id="ref-MichaelsDoubtTheirProduct2008" class="csl-entry">
Michaels, David. 2008. <em>Doubt is their product how industry’s assault on science threatens your health</em>. Oxford: Oxford Univ. Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-SuryanarayananVanishingBeesScience2016" class="csl-entry">
Suryanarayanan, Sainath, and Daniel Lee Kleinman. 2016. <em>Vanishing Bees: Science, Politics, and Honeybee Health</em>. Rutgers University Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-WynneSheepfarmingChernobylCase1989" class="csl-entry">
Wynne, Brian. 1989. <span>“Sheepfarming After Chernobyl: A Case Study in Communicating Scientific Information.”</span> <em>Environment: Science and Policy for Sustainable Development</em> 31 (2): 10–39. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00139157.1989.9928930">https://doi.org/10.1080/00139157.1989.9928930</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-09-20-power.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Misinformation and trustworthiness: Frenemies in the analysis of public scientific controversies</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-09-08-misinfo.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">Lewandowsky et al. (2022)</span> examine public scientific controversies through two contrasting “lenses” or analytical frameworks, using Covid-19 as their primary case study. The first lens, “science denial,” is pretty explicitly scientistic: in cases such as “the link between AIDS and HIV, climate change, evolution, and other clearly established scientific facts,”</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>absent new evidence, dissent from the scientifically accepted position cannot be supported by legitimate evidence and theorizing but must necessarily—that is, in virtually all instances—involve misleading or flawed argumentation. <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 31)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>There are some qualifiers in this particular quotation — “absent new evidence” and “<em>virtually</em> all instances” — but in other places these are dropped: “The rules of scientific evidence formation and argumentation are inescapable and cannot be discarded or side-stepped for political expediency” <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 32)</span> This lens explains public scientific controversies by appealing to a combination of irrationality and disinformation/propaganda.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">Lewandowsky et al. (2022)</span> recognize the technocratic implications of the “science denial” lens:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>this insistence on quality of argumentation may seemingly curtail the public’s involvement in any scientifically informed debate. After all, members of the public are often nonexperts on topics and issues whose outcomes affect their lives. <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 32)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Their first “solution” to this problem is to communicate “scientific issues” using “stories or pictures” <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 32)</span>. The second “solution” is a segue into the second lens.</p>
<hr>
<p>The “trust” lens explains controversies by appealing to the ways that “people differ in how much trust they put on various information sources (e.g., scientists vs.&nbsp;their neighbor on social media)” <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 33)</span>. Further, the lens recognizes that differences in trust can be due to differences in <em>trustworthiness</em>.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Ethnic minorities, for example, have historically been discriminated against in the health care system. Western countries, especially those with colonial histo- ries, have also damaged people’s trust in medical treatments through their previ- ous mistreatment of indigenous populations (Lowes and Montero 2021) and misuse of vaccination centers, for example, by the CIA in its hunt for Osama bin Laden (Reardon 2011). <strong>It is unsurprising that people would question scientific evidence communicated by the same institutions that caused them harm or deceived them in the past</strong> (Jamison, Quinn, and Freimuth 2019). <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 33, my emphasis)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>To elaborate this a little more, it might be helpful to make a three-way distinction, between (a) (occurrent) trust, (b) perceived trustworthiness, and (c) actual trustworthiness. A potential trustee might satisfy criteria for trustworthiness, but be incorrectly perceived to be untrustworthy by the potential trustor. For example, under the influence of politicization campaigns, many US conservatives might incorrectly believe climate scientists to be more interested in their own careers than the public interest, and thus incorrectly perceive climate scientists to be untrustworthy.</p>
<p>The “trust” lens implies that “appreciation of why evidence is mistrusted in these communities is essential” and the importance of “regain[ing] trust rather than dismiss[ing] beliefs based on lived experience as simple denialism” <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 33)</span>.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">Lewandowsky et al. (2022)</span> attempt to bring these two lenses together. Understanding why a group’s “cultural background or lived experience” undermines the trustworthiness of mainstream institutions “can provide pointers as to why [they] engage[] in (or fall[] for)” irrationality and disinformation <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 34)</span>. In addition (or perhaps “specifically”), understanding the causes of trustworthiness failures “can reveal shortcomings in the scientific process or evidence base …. analysis of those arguments can provide valuable pointers to underlying issues—such as lacking representation in medical research—that can be addressed by suitable policies or remedial research” <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 34)</span>.</p>
<p>I would add that the example of incorrectly perceiving climate scientists to be untrustworthy suggests that perceived untrustworthiness and misinformation can be co-producing. Climate propagandists have not only promulgated “first order” misinformation about climate change (“it’s all natural variation”) but also “second order” misinformation about climate <em>scientists</em> (“they’ll say whatever it takes to get published”).</p>
<hr>
<p>Unfortunately, in their final section, “Recommendations,” <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">Lewandowsky et al. (2022)</span> seem to revert back to the “science denial” lens alone. Their two primary recommendations are that “misleading and inappropriate argumentation must be identified” and that “when misleading arguments have been identified, they can be used to ‘inoculate’ the public against their ill effects” <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 35)</span>. The “trust” lens’ emphasis on understanding why scientific institutions might not be (perceived to be) trustworthy has all but disappeared. The “trust” lens does get one paragraph, arguing that “Policies that take into account the reasons underlying misleading arguments can be more effective than those agnostic about these reasons” and that emphasizing “‘winning’ an argument” is unlikely to be successful” <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 35)</span>. But the final sentence asserts that deliberation “can be achieved” “only when misleading arguments can be identified and rejected” <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022">(Lewandowsky et al. 2022, 35)</span>, that is, only when “science” wins the argument.</p>
<hr>
<p>I really like the way this piece contrasts two common frameworks for understanding public scientific controversies. The scientistic and technocratic implications of the “science denial”/misinformation framework are on full display, which is useful for illustrating why I typically dislike this framework and find it, at best, incomplete. And the attempt to synthesize the two frameworks is useful: as you can see, it prompted me to think about how I understand the role of propaganda and misinformation in my analysis of controversies.</p>
<p>But that “Recommendations” section. To me, the paper reads like there were two sets of authors here. One set working with the misinfo framework, the other with the trustworthiness framework. The trustworthiness folks made a reasonable effort to integrate trustworthiness and misinformation in their section. But the misinfo folks ignored this, relying just on their framework to write the concluding section.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-LewandowskyWhenScienceBecomes2022" class="csl-entry">
Lewandowsky, Stephan, Konstantinos Armaos, Hendrik Bruns, Philipp Schmid, Dawn Liu Holford, Ulrike Hahn, Ahmed Al-Rawi, Sunita Sah, and John Cook. 2022. <span>“When Science Becomes Embroiled in Conflict: Recognizing the Public’s Need for Debate While Combating Conspiracies and Misinformation.”</span> <em>The ANNALS of the American Academy of Political and Social Science</em> 700 (1): 26–40. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/00027162221084663">https://doi.org/10.1177/00027162221084663</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-09-08-misinfo.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Revisiting the Nazi Problem</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-06-07-nazi-problem.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In theory this will be a quick post. In theory.</p>
<p>At a conference a couple of weeks ago, I was talking (read: complaining) about how, as far as I’m aware, no one has ever really responded to the “Nazi Problem,” a concern about Longino’s conception of objectivity raised by Natalia Baeza in a grad seminar she and I took with Janet Kourany at Notre Dame circa 2007 and that I wrote up in my first publication a few years later <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksLonginoConceptionObjectivity2011">(Hicks 2011)</span>. Yet, with the revitalization of race science over the last 8 years or so, the Nazi Problem is even more urgent today than it was in 2007-ish. Heather Douglas told me she had a brief solution in a recent paper of hers <span class="citation" data-cites="DouglasDifferentiatingScientificInquiry2023">(Douglas 2023)</span>. In this post, after summarizing the Nazi Problem, I’ll present Douglas’ solution and my response.</p>
<p>A key implication of Longino’s conception of objectivity is that it requires the active cultivation of a wide range of perspectives, in order to ensure the critical scrutiny of implicit assumptions made by the scientific mainstream. For Longino this provides an epistemic argument for the active cultivation of women (feminist) and POC (antiracist) scientists. The “Nazi Problem” is that this reasoning seems to apply equally to Nazi/sexist/racist scientists, and therefore it seems that Longino’s account of objectivity requires actively cultivating them as well.</p>
<p>The primary solution to the Nazi Problem that I consider in the paper<sup>1</sup> was to point out an incompatibility between the political liberalism built into Longino’s account — ideas like formal (epistemic) equality — and Nazi anti-liberalism. A sexist can’t authentically comply with norms that require them to treat women as equals, and so we just qualify Longino’s account by saying that it doesn’t require the active cultivation of inauthentic perspectives. On the few occasions where people have responded to the Nazi Problem in print, this is the response they give <span class="citation" data-cites="RolinCanSocialDiversity2017">(for example, Rolin 2017, 123–24)</span>.</p>
<p>The problem with this response, for me, is that it also rules out feminist standpoint theory. Because they think certain standpoints are epistemically advantaged, standpoint theorists also can’t authentically comply with norms that require them to treat disadvantaged standpoints as formal epistemic equals. I make a similar point about the commitment to neutrality between comprehensive conceptions of the good life and communitarian feminists.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="DouglasDifferentiatingScientificInquiry2023">Douglas (2023)</span>’s response to the Nazi Problem is raised in the context of identifying some key differences between inquiry (science) and democratic politics. A key contribution in this paper is the notion of <em>inquirer façades</em>, “faking one of the central norms of inquiry without following through on its demands.” Douglas proposes that “When inquirer facades are discovered, they can be legitimately ignored by those within the space of inquiry” <span class="citation" data-cites="DouglasDifferentiatingScientificInquiry2023">(Douglas 2023, 133)</span>.<sup>2</sup> Here’s Douglas on the Nazi Problem:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>One might worry, though, that fostering diversity can include bringing into the space of inquiry ideological views impervious to criticism (Hicks, 2011). However, if we keep in mind that all participants in the space of inquiry must be responsive to criticism (norm 2), this concern is alleviated. The ideologically pre-committed cannot survive the demands of criticism and response for long, revealing the fact that they are inquirer facades and thus can be legitimately ignored within the space of inquiry. <span class="citation" data-cites="DouglasDifferentiatingScientificInquiry2023">(Douglas 2023, 136)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have four comments. My first point is that Douglas has reframed the Nazi Problem in terms of closed-mindedness or “dogmatism.”<sup>3</sup> But, like <span class="citation" data-cites="AlcoffCommentaryElizabethAnderson2006">Alcoff (2006)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="YapFeministRadicalEmpiricism2015">Yap (2015)</span>, I don’t regard closed-mindedness as such a severe vice. As Yap puts it, “values such as respecting women’s autonomy and self-determination should be seen as basic commitments and not ‘up for grabs’ in the same kind of way” as our taste in music <span class="citation" data-cites="YapFeministRadicalEmpiricism2015">(Yap 2015, 5)</span>.</p>
<p>Second, rather than thinking the problem with Nazis is that they’re closed-minded, the problem with Nazis is that they’re Nazis. They hold odious racist, sexist, and anti-democratic beliefs, and often embrace offensive political violence as a means of achieving political power.<sup>4</sup></p>
<p>Third, the history of behavior genetics shows how a scientific community can protect racists and sexists by deflecting values-based critique while still responding to technical criticism <span class="citation" data-cites="PanofskyMisbehavingScienceControversy2014">(Panofsky 2014)</span>. Panofsky argues that, prior to Jensen’s 1969 “How Much Can We Boost IQ and Scholastic Achievement?” paper, behavior geneticists explicitly marginalized eugenics and race science, with the goal of avoiding controversy and having their work compared to Nazi race science <span class="citation" data-cites="PanofskyMisbehavingScienceControversy2014">(Panofsky 2014 ch.&nbsp;2)</span>. Consequently many behavior geneticists were at least deeply uncomfortable with the controversy (and Nazi comparisons) that Jensen attracted <span class="citation" data-cites="PanofskyMisbehavingScienceControversy2014">(Panofsky 2014, 80)</span>. However, in reaction to broad criticisms of behavior genetics <em>as such</em> by Lewontin, Kamin, and other critics, behavior geneticists adopted a kind of fortress mentality — with the field under constant threat of repression by political radicals <span class="citation" data-cites="PanofskyMisbehavingScienceControversy2014">(Panofsky 2014, 114)</span> — along with an “absolutist interpretation of intellectual freedom” that did not include any sense of social responsibility for, for example, racist appropriations of behavior genetics research <span class="citation" data-cites="PanofskyMisbehavingScienceControversy2014">(Panofsky 2014, 194–97)</span>. At the same time, behavior geneticists — including those who continue to study intelligence and race — have at least somewhat engaged with technical critiques, at least nominally rejecting a strong hereditarianism in favor of gene-environment interactions, and shifting from twin studies to GWAS (genome-wide association studies) and polygenic indices as genomics technology has developed <span class="citation" data-cites="PanofskyMisbehavingScienceControversy2014">(Panofsky 2014 ch.&nbsp;6)</span>. These changes in the field are regarded as inadequate by many critics, both internal <span class="citation" data-cites="TurkheimerThisTimeMean2022">(Turkheimer 2022)</span> and external <span class="citation" data-cites="DownesChangesHeritabilityUnpredictable2022">(Downes and Kaplan 2022)</span>. But they do give behavior geneticists ground — however thin — to claim that race-and-intelligence researchers are responsive to criticism.</p>
<p>More generally, if Longino’s account can justify excluding Nazis who are closed-minded and/or not responsive to criticism, it would still seem to require actively cultivating Nazis, so long as they’re open-minded and engage in uptake. And, over the past decade or so, right-wing intellectuals and provocateurs — including proponents of race science — have adopted at least the posture of open-mindedness and the value of debate and free speech <span class="citation" data-cites="RobinCriticClownTale2017 ReiheldGimletEyeJournal2018 TaylorFreeSpeechHypocrisy2018">(Robin 2017; Reiheld 2018; Taylor 2018)</span>.</p>
<p>Fourth and finally, I didn’t develop my own solution to the Nazi Problem in <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksLonginoConceptionObjectivity2011">Hicks (2011)</span>. A decade and change later, my own solution would align with Douglas’ recognition that “Both societal and epistemic responsibilities generate reasons for excluding some topics and methods from legitimate inquiry” <span class="citation" data-cites="DouglasDifferentiatingScientificInquiry2023">(Douglas 2023, 129)</span>. Indeed, Douglas discusses the case of behavior genetics:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Current debates over restraints often combine moral, political, and epistemic concerns. Consider the debate over the legitimacy of research on race-based or gender-based intelligence. The history of such work has been so consistently shoddy that doubts have been raised about whether this is an epistemically productive line of inquiry (Rose, 2009). Further, <strong>it has been so socially harmful that it may not be unreasonable to declare such work outside the space of legitimate inquiry at this point</strong> (Kourany, 2016). Merely pointing to generic scientific freedom or the need to pursue truth is inadequate in the face of these concerns (Ceci &amp; Williams, 2009). Well-formed and reasoned restraints on the space of inquiry have a long history of legitimacy. <span class="citation" data-cites="DouglasDifferentiatingScientificInquiry2023">(Douglas 2023, 130–31, my emphasis)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve emphasized the moral argument, which comes closest to the grounds on which I would exclude racists and sexists. But rather than the downstream social harms of research, I would point directly to the racism and sexism itself. These values — and acting in line with them — are odious and not to be tolerated <span class="citation" data-cites="SchroederLimitsDemocratizingScience2022">(Schroeder 2022)</span>. Nearly 80 years after the formal demise of Nazism, there is good reason why it is almost universally reviled.</p>
<p>The problem with Nazis is that they are Nazis, and this is also the reason why we should not actively cultivate them, in science or elsewhere.</p>





<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-AlcoffCommentaryElizabethAnderson2006" class="csl-entry">
Alcoff, Linda Martín. 2006. <span>“Commentary on Elizabeth Anderson’s <span>‘Uses of Value Judgments in Science’</span>.”</span> <em>Symposia on Gender, Race and Philosophy</em> 2 (1). <a href="https://sgrponline.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/alcoff0106-1.pdf">https://sgrponline.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/alcoff0106-1.pdf</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-DouglasDifferentiatingScientificInquiry2023" class="csl-entry">
Douglas, Heather. 2023. <span>“Differentiating Scientific Inquiry and Politics.”</span> <em>Philosophy</em> 98 (2): 123–46. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0031819122000432">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0031819122000432</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-DownesChangesHeritabilityUnpredictable2022" class="csl-entry">
Downes, Stephen M., and Jonathan Michael Kaplan. 2022. <span>“Changes in Heritability: Unpredictable and of Limited Use.”</span> <em>Behavioral and Brain Sciences</em> 45 (January): e159. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0140525X2100159X">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0140525X2100159X</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksLonginoConceptionObjectivity2011" class="csl-entry">
Hicks, Daniel J. 2011. <span>“Is Longino’s Conception of Objectivity Feminist?”</span> <em>Hypatia: A Journal of Feminist Philosophy</em> 26 (2): 333–51. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1527-2001.2010.01160.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1527-2001.2010.01160.x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksWhenVirtuesAre2022" class="csl-entry">
———. 2022. <span>“When Virtues are Vices: <span>‘Anti-Science’</span> Epistemic Values in Environmental Politics.”</span> <em>Philosophy, Theory, and Practice in Biology</em> 14 (0). <a href="https://doi.org/10.3998/.2629">https://doi.org/10.3998/.2629</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-PanofskyMisbehavingScienceControversy2014" class="csl-entry">
Panofsky, Aaron. 2014. <em>Misbehaving Science: Controversy and the Development of Behavior Genetics</em>. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press. <a href="https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/M/bo16124298.html">https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/M/bo16124298.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ReiheldGimletEyeJournal2018" class="csl-entry">
Reiheld, Alison. 2018. <span>“A Gimlet Eye: The Journal of Controversial Ideas and Jonathan Anomaly’s <span>‘Defending Eugenics’</span> (Guest Post).”</span> Discrimination and Disadvantage. November 16, 2018. <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210227220754/https://philosophycommons.typepad.com/disability_and_disadvanta/2018/11/a-gimlet-eye-a-journal-of-controversial-ideas-and-jonathon-anomalys-defending-eugenics.html">https://web.archive.org/web/20210227220754/https://philosophycommons.typepad.com/disability_and_disadvanta/2018/11/a-gimlet-eye-a-journal-of-controversial-ideas-and-jonathon-anomalys-defending-eugenics.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-RobinCriticClownTale2017" class="csl-entry">
Robin, Corey. 2017. <span>“The Critic and the Clown: A Tale of Free Speech at Berkeley.”</span> September 11, 2017. <a href="http://coreyrobin.com/2017/09/11/the-critic-and-the-clown-a-tale-of-free-speech-at-berkeley/">http://coreyrobin.com/2017/09/11/the-critic-and-the-clown-a-tale-of-free-speech-at-berkeley/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-RolinCanSocialDiversity2017" class="csl-entry">
Rolin, Kristina. 2017. <span>“Can Social Diversity Be Best Incorporated into Science by Adopting the Social Value Management Ideal?”</span> In <em>Current Controversies in Values and Science</em>, edited by Kevin C. Elliott and Daniel Steel, 1 edition, 113–29. Routledge.
</div>
<div id="ref-SchroederLimitsDemocratizingScience2022" class="csl-entry">
Schroeder, S. Andrew. 2022. <span>“The Limits of Democratizing Science: When Scientists Should Ignore the Public.”</span> <em>Philosophy of Science</em> 89 (5): 1034–43. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/psa.2022.54">https://doi.org/10.1017/psa.2022.54</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-TaylorFreeSpeechHypocrisy2018" class="csl-entry">
Taylor, Keeanga-Yamahtta. 2018. <span>“The <span>‘Free Speech’</span> Hypocrisy of Right-Wing Media.”</span> <em>The New York Times</em>, January 20, 2018, sec. Opinion. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/08/14/opinion/the-free-speech-hypocrisy-of-right-wing-media.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2017/08/14/opinion/the-free-speech-hypocrisy-of-right-wing-media.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-TurkheimerThisTimeMean2022" class="csl-entry">
Turkheimer, Eric. 2022. <span>“This Time I Mean It: The Nature–Nurture Debate Is Over.”</span> <em>Behavioral and Brain Sciences</em> 45 (January): e177. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0140525X21001771">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0140525X21001771</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-YapFeministRadicalEmpiricism2015" class="csl-entry">
Yap, Audrey. 2015. <span>“Feminist Radical Empiricism, Values, and Evidence.”</span> <em>Hypatia</em>, November, n/a–. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/hypa.12221">https://doi.org/10.1111/hypa.12221</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>which was my response to Natalia during seminar↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>One thing that’s a little unclear to me is the extent to which this definition depends on intentions or authenticity rather than behavior. “Faking” suggests something like inauthenticity, a mismatch between actual and voiced commitments, that I think can be difficult to get at empirically <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksWhenVirtuesAre2022">(Hicks 2022, 4n3)</span>. But norm compliance is often operationalized in behavior. For example, as I understand it liability in tort law generally doesn’t depend on intentions or anything else about mental states.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I dislike this term, because I suspect etymologically it’s entangled with anti-Catholicism.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>I include “offensive” here to leave room for views, such as those of Malcolm X and Franz Fanon, that political violence might be necessary for community self-defense against a violently oppressive state.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-06-07-nazi-problem.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New preprint: tmfast fits topic models fast</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-05-04-tmfast.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Yesterday I published a new preprint on the arXiv: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.01535">“<code>tmfast</code> fits topic models fast”</a>. Here’s the abstract:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><code>tmfast</code> is an R package for fitting topic models using a fast algorithm based on partial PCA and the varimax rotation. After providing mathematical background to the method, we present two examples, using a simulated corpus and aggregated works of a selection of authors from the long nineteenth century, and compare the quality of the fitted models to a standard topic modeling package.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The package itself is available <a href="https://github.com/dhicks/tmfast">on Github</a>.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-05-04-tmfast.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Anarchy and Covid-19</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-04-12-anarchy-covid19.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I started working on this two or three weeks ago, got about 1500 words in, and then had to shelve it to deal with a minor deluge of grading and some other things. I thought I would be able to pick it back up, but I’ve lost the thread. In the “writer’s notebook” spirit of this project, I’m just going to post it.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>In our Facebook discussion of <a href="2023-04-07-pluralism-problems">my last post</a>, Matt Brown referred to me a more recent paper of his on Feyerabend <span class="citation" data-cites="BrownExpertiseLessonFeyerabend2021">(Brown 2021)</span>. I really like this paper, and want to focus on it instead of the older one.</p>
<p>Brown discusses Feyerabend’s critique of expertise from “How to Defend Society against Science” <span class="citation" data-cites="FeyerabendHowDefendSociety1975">(Feyerabend 1975)</span> and <em>Science in a Free Society</em> [<span class="citation" data-cites="FeyerabendScienceFreeSociety2017">Feyerabend (2017)</span>; originally published 1978 . After tying Feyerabend’s critique to the current literature on science, values, and policy, and noting that Feyerabend had some overly simplistic political philosophy in the ’70s (which don’t really impact the argument Brown is interested in), Brown summarizes the critique of expertise as a sequence of “four increasingly radical claims about science and its place in society that, together, point toward a decentering of experts in society and a rejection of expert authority” (195).</p>
<p>In this post, I want to read these four claims together with <span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">Lee et al. (2021)</span>, a fantastic study of the data analysis practices of Covid-19 skeptics. If you haven’t read this paper before, I can’t recommend it enough. <span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">Lee et al. (2021)</span> challenge the widespread (among natural scientists and public health official) deficit model of public scientific controversies, which blames controversies on public ignorance. Examining social media communications from 2020, <span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">Lee et al. (2021)</span> show that “anti-mask groups on Twitter often create polished counter-visualizations that would not be out of place in scientific papers, health department reports, and publications like the Financial Times” and that “these groups leverage the language of scientific rigor—being critical about data sources, explicitly stating analytical limitations of specific models, and more—in order to support ending public health restrictions despite the consensus of the scientific establishment” <span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">(Lee et al. 2021, 1–2)</span>. I think this is a useful test case for distinguishing my own views from those of both Feyerabend and Brown.</p>
<section id="citizens-can-and-should-evaluate-expert-opinion" class="level1">
<h1>Citizens can and should evaluate expert opinion</h1>
<p>Brown discusses three arguments that Feyerabend gives for this first claim. I agree with this claim, and find the second and third argument most compelling.<sup>1</sup></p>
<p>The second argument is that public<sup>2</sup> evaluation of expert opinion will “contribute to … the development of a mature democratic citizenry” and that “the learning and maturation necessary for citizens to become wise or skillful public participants requires … that they be allowed to try and, perhaps, do poorly” (196). I actually don’t have much to say about this here; I’m noting it because I think it fits well with the broader project on experts as epistemic representatives, where part of the good of representation is actually promoting the democratic capacities of the constituency.</p>
<p>The third argument is that “motivated ‘laymen,’ in fact, can be competent enough to make good decisions regarding scientific information: ‘science is not beyond the natural shrewdness of the human race’” (196, quoting Feyerabend). This is something I emphasize with my students: that members of the general public are capable of getting together, educating themselves (collectively — this will be important later), and developing incisive technical critiques of credentialed expertise. My standard examples are ACT-UP <span class="citation" data-cites="EpsteinImpureScience1996">(Epstein 1996)</span> and environmental justice movements <span class="citation" data-cites="OttingerTechnoscienceEnvironmentalJustice2011">(Ottinger and Cohen 2011)</span>. <span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">Lee et al. (2021)</span> find that members of the Covid-19 skeptic movement “provide[d] numerous tutorials on how to access government health data” and construct visualizations and perform analyses in ways that “encourage[d] … [social media] followers to begin their own data analysis projects” (11).</p>
</section>
<section id="citizens-can-and-should-supervise-science" class="level1">
<h1>Citizens can and should supervise science</h1>
<p>I don’t like the word “supervise” here; Brown discusses an important ambiguity in this term later (201). Brown gives a more precise gloss on the second claim, albeit in a way that won’t work as a section header: “According to Feyerabend, we should elect committees of non-experts to regularly subject scientists and their work to review before it is put to social use” (197).</p>
<p>The primary argument for this second claim comes from a view that Feyerabend shares with Kuhn and Lakatos, that “science contains some necessarily presumptive, dogmatic element that both makes scientific progress possible” but that also obstructs what Feyerabend calls “unchained curiosity” (198). As philosophers of science understand this thought today, scientific practice requires background assumptions, conceptual frameworks, and methodological standards that are often arbitrary, unjustified, left implicit, and/or known to be false. This epistemic infrastructure is all but necessary even to pose research questions and design data collection plans, and so well-functioning scientific communities have norms and enforcement mechanisms (often implicit) that compel their members to accept it. But there is a risk of mismatch, between the epistemic infrastructure developed by a group of experts to address the concerns they find interesting, and the practical needs of policymakers and publics. Feyerabend emphasizes the role of iconoclasts and outsiders in challenging the adequacy of the epistemic infrastructure of the scientific establishment.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">Lee et al. (2021)</span> provide an example of this with</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>an ongoing animated debate within these groups about which metrics matter. Some users contend that deaths, not cases, should be the ultimate arbiter in policy decisions, since case rates are easily “manipulated” (e.g., with increased testing) and do not necessarily signal severe health problems (people can be asymptomatic). (11)</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="line-block">One might argue that case rates are an appropriate metric for the health care system, insofar as a rise in case rates is a leading indicator of a rise of hospital admissions a week or two into the future. This assumes that some significant fraction of cases will be sufficiently severe to lead to hospital admissions. But Covid-19 skeptics are skeptical of exactly this fraction. In their eyes, the central question is whether Covid-19 is as severe as the scientific establishment claims. Since death is an unambiguous measure of severity, arguably death rates are a better metric for what they see as the central question. So here we might be able to see a mismatch between the epistemic infrastructure of the experts and that of (the Covid-19 skeptical section of) the public.</div>
<p>In <a href="2023-04-07-pluralism-problems">my last post</a> I made some points about reliability vs.&nbsp;relevance. Even if the methods used by the scientific community are highly reliable (truth-apt, for some non-pragmatic correspondence conception of truth), they’re not necessarily relevant to the epistemic and practical needs of the broader public(s). <span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">Lee et al. (2021)</span> also have a few examples of Covid-19 skeptics challenging the reliability of the scientific establishment. They quote one skeptic:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You can’t simply subtract the current death tally from the typical value for this time of year and attribute the difference to Covid,” a user wrote. “Because of the actions of our governments, we are actually causing excess deaths. Want to kill an old person quickly? Take away their human interaction and contact.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="line-block">This skeptic is arguing that <a href="https://kieranhealy.org/blog/archives/2020/10/01/walk-the-walk/">simple calculations of excess deaths due to the pandemic</a> cannot distinguish deaths due to Covid-19 and deaths due to Covid-19 mitigation policies, and thus these methods are not reliable for estimating deaths due to Covid-19. I suspect almost all public health officials already understood this problem. But I would agree with Feyerabend that it’s appropriate for members of the public to ask public health officials whether and how they’ve taken this confounding into account.</div>
</section>
<section id="science-is-just-another-ideology-or-interest-group" class="level1">
<h1>Science Is Just Another Ideology or Interest Group</h1>
<p>This is where I start to diverge from Feyerabend and the Covid-19 skeptics. <span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">Lee et al. (2021)</span> argue that Covid-19 skeptics “seek to identify bias by being critical about specific profit motives that come from releasing (or suppressing) specific kinds of information,” (12) especially the interests of the pharmaceutical industry (12) and state authorities (11). That is, they see public health officials and the mainstream scientific community as corrupted, pursuing power and wealth rather than truth and health. But this is not a rejection of science as such: Covid-19 skeptics “use ‘data-driven’ narratives to justify their heterodox beliefs” (10), creating data visualizations, appealing to mainstream epistemic values such as data validation, data quality, and the need for control groups, and touting their own formal scientific credentials (10-12). As <span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">Lee et al. (2021)</span> put it, “their approach to the pandemic is grounded in a more scientific rigor, not less,”</p>
<p>Brown’s discussion of Feyerabend’s view is biographical:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Feyerabend taught at the University of California, Berkeley during the desegregation of public education in the United States and the attendant increase in non-white enrollments at Berkeley …. He came to see his educational role as essentially oppressive, pushing “reflections of the conceit of a small group who had succeeded in enslaving everyone else with their ideas,” and to find the very idea revolting …. The problem was that the ideology of the privileged remained centered. (199)</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="line-block">And in <a href="2023-04-07-pluralism-problems">my last post</a> I wrote</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In other words, the “we” who find ourselves in a problematic situation can often be diverse in ways that lead “us” to different ways of understanding the nature of the problem. Giving “science” priority or greater standing over other considerations amounts to giving one group or perspective priority over the others.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="line-block">I even cited “How to Defend Society against Science” here. So why do I say that I diverge from Feyerabend and the Covid-19 skeptics here?</div>
<p>Feminist scientists and HPSTSers have long held a nuanced attitude towards science, which I some gloss as “<em>exactly</em> one and a half cheers for science.”</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In exposing widespread, largely unremarked androcentric and sexist bias, feminists demonstrate that good science, even our best science, can be deeply structured by the values and interests of its makers …. Feminists engage the sciences not only as critics of bias and partiality but also as practitioners who recognize that systematic empirical inquiry has an indispensable role to play in understanding and changing oppressive conditions …. [T]he goal of understanding and changing conditions of life that disadvantage women requires as much empirical accuracy and explanatory precision as scientific inquiry can afford. <span class="citation" data-cites="WylieComingTermsValues2007">(Wylie and Hankinson Nelson 2007, 59)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="line-block">On the one hand, science has often been (and continues to be) a powerful tool of oppression, wielded against women and other oppressed groups. On the other hand, science can also be a powerful tool of justice, especially when those same groups find ways to turn the methods of scientific inquiry back on themselves, systematically studying systems of oppression and the role that science has played in them. (This — presented in Deweyan terms — is how I proposed to avoid anything-goes relativism in the previous post.)</div>
<p>Feyerabend was evidently sensitive to the first point here. But it seems to me that he missed the second point, falling into an irremediable cynicism about science and its role(s) in society.</p>
</section>
<section id="science-should-be-separated-from-the-state" class="level1">
<h1>Science Should Be Separated from the State</h1>
<p>Building off the previous point, Feyerabend’s argument here is an analogy with religion. Science, like religion, is just another interest group or ideology; respecting the fact of reasonable pluralism, liberal democracies formally separate religion and state power; and therefore liberal democracies should formally separate science and state power. Science should have no special standing or influence in policymaking, but also should be protected from excessive state interference.</p>
<p>At this point Brown revisits the notion of “supervise” from the second claim, that the public should supervise science. If “supervise” is interpreted as regulatory oversight and the exercise of state authority, then there’s a tension between the second claim and the idea that science, like religion, is a private activity and as such the state shouldn’t interfere with it. But if “supervise” is interpreted as “elect[ing] committees of non-experts to regularly subject scientists and their work to review <em>before it is put to social use</em>” (197, my emphasis) then there’s no tension. The public supervises the moment at which scientific findings are communicated to policymakers as advice. Scientists can do whatever they want on their side of the science-policy wall; it’s passage through the wall that’s subject to formal scrutiny and review.</p>
<p>This picture becomes much more complicated when the scientists in question are government employees, such as public health officials managing the collection, transmission, and publication of pandemic data. But perhaps Feyerabend’s view is that government employees shouldn’t be doing this kind of work. Managing public health is no more the state’s business than managing spiritual health. In this way, Feyerabend’s epistemic anarchism would seem to lead to political anarchism.</p>
<hr>
<p>I teach <span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">Lee et al. (2021)</span> in a data science course open to any graduate student in quantitative social science. A couple of years ago, one of the students noted that Covid-19 skeptics have an “individualistic epistemology.” As <span class="citation" data-cites="LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021">Lee et al. (2021)</span> put it, “anti-maskers value unmediated access to information and privilege personal research and direct reading over ‘expert’ interpretations.” I would suggest that this reflects an ideal from (right-) libertarian political philosophy, of self-reliance and independence (non-dependence) on others.</p>
<p>But this ideal is incompatible with the way the community of Covid-19 skeptics actually operates. Community members teach each other how to find and work with data, reinforce perceptions of state and scientific corruption, develop shared interpretations of their custom visualizations, and promote counterexperts (credentialed or not) with favorable views.</p>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-BrownExpertiseLessonFeyerabend2021" class="csl-entry">
Brown, Matthew J. 2021. <span>“Against Expertise: A Lesson from Feyerabend’s Science in a Free Society?”</span> In <em>Interpreting Feyerabend: Critical Essays</em>, edited by Jamie Shaw and Karim Bschir, 191–212. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/9781108575102.011">https://doi.org/10.1017/9781108575102.011</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-EpsteinImpureScience1996" class="csl-entry">
Epstein, Steven. 1996. <em>Impure Science</em>. AIDS, Activism, and the Politics of Knowledge. Berkeley, Los Angeles, and Oxford: University of California Press. <a href="http://books.google.ca/books?id=kZOso0FMsrMC&amp;pg=PA39&amp;dq=intitle:Impure+Science+inauthor:epstein&amp;hl=&amp;cd=1&amp;source=gbs_api">http://books.google.ca/books?id=kZOso0FMsrMC&amp;pg=PA39&amp;dq=intitle:Impure+Science+inauthor:epstein&amp;hl=&amp;cd=1&amp;source=gbs_api</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-FeyerabendHowDefendSociety1975" class="csl-entry">
Feyerabend, Paul. 1975. <span>“How to Defend Society Against Science.”</span> <em>Radical Philosophy</em>, no. 011 (Summer): 3–8.
</div>
<div id="ref-FeyerabendScienceFreeSociety2017" class="csl-entry">
———. 2017. <em>Science in a Free Society</em>. Verso Books.
</div>
<div id="ref-LeeViralVisualizationsHow2021" class="csl-entry">
Lee, Crystal, Tanya Yang, Gabrielle Inchoco, Graham M. Jones, and Arvind Satyanarayan. 2021. <span>“Viral Visualizations: How Coronavirus Skeptics Use Orthodox Data Practices to Promote Unorthodox Science Online.”</span> <em>Proceedings of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</em>, May, 1–18. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3411764.3445211">https://doi.org/10.1145/3411764.3445211</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-OttingerTechnoscienceEnvironmentalJustice2011" class="csl-entry">
Ottinger, Gwen, and Benjamin R. Cohen, eds. 2011. <em>Technoscience and Environmental Justice: Expert Cultures in a Grassroots Movement</em>. Urban and Industrial Environments. Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-WylieComingTermsValues2007" class="csl-entry">
Wylie, Alison, and Lynn Hankinson Nelson. 2007. <span>“Coming to Terms with the Values of Science: Insights from Feminist Science Studies Scholarship.”</span> In <em>Value-Free Science?</em>, edited by Harold Kincaid, John Dupré, and Alison Wylie, 58–86. Oxford University Press. <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=9Nqppv6uq7oC">http://books.google.com/books?id=9Nqppv6uq7oC</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>The first is based on Mill’s argument in chapter 2 of <em>On Liberty</em>. My thoughts about this argument are complex and not what I’m interested in here.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Brown uses “citizen” 45 times in the paper, compared to 28 uses of “public.” I’m guessing this is following Feyerabend. But because of my location in California’s Central Valley, with its large population of migrant and often undocumented farmworkers, I prefer the broader term.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-04-12-anarchy-covid19.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pluralism about problematic situations</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-04-07-pluralism-problems.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Matt Brown has some commentary <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hicks.daniel.j/posts/pfbid0Z31gfZEy2EgeYCGyBdD3XXfLVUQHJXW2gjjE1jwFQWQmuWQSCmRTtMon6PRDx4Q8l?comment_id=1392646594824355&amp;notif_id=1680900361004955&amp;notif_t=feed_comment&amp;ref=notif">here</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>I’ve been invited to give <a href="https://values.utdallas.edu/2022/12/20/2023-conference/">a keynote</a> on Matt Brown’s work at the UT Dallas conference in May. <span class="citation" data-cites="BrownDemocraticControlScientific2013">Brown (2013)</span> fits with my current project (as seen in the recent blog posts), so this post is maybe the first of a sub-series of posts on his paper. All headless citations are to <span class="citation" data-cites="BrownDemocraticControlScientific2013">Brown (2013)</span>.</p>
<p>Brown first argues that there is a tension between the autonomy (lack of accountability) of science and its social and political authority in a democratic society. He quotes Douglas:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>[A]n autonomous and authoritative science is intolerable …. A fully autonomous and authoritative science is too powerful, with no attendant responsibility <span class="citation" data-cites="DouglasSciencePolicyValuefree2009">(Douglas 2009, 7–8, as quoted by Brown, 481)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Scholars and activists who have been sensitive to this tension — he names Feyerabend and STS scholars; we could include many feminists, anti-racists, and Marxists — “have tended to challenge the … authority of science …. weakening or denying the existence of expertise in politics” (481). This is objectionable because it amounts to “giv[ing] up tools in policy-making that we cannot do without, … given the remarkable success of science” (481-2).</p>
<p>Here, and elsewhere in the paper, Brown links the epistemic credibility or <em>reliability</em> of science to its political authority. Science should have authority in policymaking because it is an especially (the most?) reliable way of producing knowledge. But the kind or degree of political authority that Brown has in mind is vague. It’s one thing to say that scientific findings or methods can be useful in many policymaking situations, and so typically there should be a deliberate effort to solicit advice from scientists; it’s another to say that science should have some kind of priority or greater standing over other considerations.</p>
<p>I argue that Brown’s own account of inquiry should lead us towards the former formulation, of science as frequently useful rather than science taking priority. On Brown’s account, inquiry (scientific or otherwise) is a systematic response to a <em>problematic situation</em>, a situation in which we (we’ll come back to this “we”) realize that our established habits fail to realize their aims. Inquiry is considered <em>successful</em> insofar as it establishes a better fit between habits and aims; this might involve developing completely new habits, tweaking old habits, and/or reconstituting the aims.</p>
<p>A number of different kinds of controversies can emerge from this simple framework. In <strong>aim controversies</strong>, parties disagree over the aims that our habits are supposed to be realizing. <strong>Diagnostic controversies</strong> concern the explanation for why the habits are failing to realize their aims. We can even have <strong>problem controversies</strong>, in which parties disagree over whether we are in a problematic situation at all. Brown gives the example of US policy debates surrounding health care reform in 2009-2010 (483-4), which featured each of these kinds of controversies.</p>
<p>When parties disagree with each other in these kinds of ways, they will disagree with each other about whether a line of inquiry should be considered <strong>relevant</strong> to a policy problem, and thus whether it should be counted as successful with respect to the problematic situation at hand. For example, consider an economic analysis that finds that a combination of employer and individual health insurance mandates and a means-tested subsidy for private insurance will tend to increase health insurance coverage. This line of inquiry might be considered successful by someone whose diagnosis of the problem with the US health care system is that private insurance is too expensive, but not by people who think the problem is a profit-driven healthcare industry or creeping government overreach. For the latter two groups of people, even if the economic analysis is highly reliable it is not relevant to developing a solution to the problem <span class="citation" data-cites="CartwrightEvidenceBasedPolicyPractical2012 HicksEpistemologicalDepthGM2015">(Cartwright and Hardie 2012; Hicks 2015)</span>.</p>
<p>In other words, the “we” who find ourselves in a problematic situation can often be diverse in ways that lead “us” to different ways of understanding the nature of the problem. Giving “science” priority or greater standing over other considerations amounts to giving one group or perspective priority over the others <span class="citation" data-cites="FeyerabendHowDefendSociety1975 LonginoCanThereBe1987 LaceyScientificResearchTechnological2014 HicksGeneticallyModifiedCrops2017">(Feyerabend 1975; Longino 1987; Lacey 2014; Hicks 2017)</span>.</p>
<p>This analysis might seem to threaten to degenerate into anything-goes relativism, with partisans cherry-picking the science that fits their preferred account of the problem <span class="citation" data-cites="SarewitzHowScienceMakes2004">(Sarewitz 2004)</span>. But I think we can avoid relativism by viewing a policy controversy as itself a problematic situation prompting inquiry. In other words, we can use scientific inquiry as a way to understand and thereby navigate political conflict, not as a cudgel that one side gets to use against the others.</p>
<p>Consider climate change. Climate scientists have raised concerns in public about the impacts of carbon dioxide emissions for over 35 years, but policy responses have been faltering at best and public attitudes seem deeply divided. Why is this, and what could be done to get a better match between the apparent problem and a policy solution? Scholars in several fields of the social sciences and humanities have tackled this question for at least 20 years, working to understand the roles of fossil fuel companies <span class="citation" data-cites="OreskesMerchantsDoubtHow2011 SupranAssessingExxonMobilClimate2017">(Oreskes and Conway 2011; Supran and Oreskes 2017)</span>; uncertainties in climate science, both real and manufactured <span class="citation" data-cites="LloydModelRobustnessConfirmatory2015">(Lloyd 2015)</span>; public perceptions of and attitudes towards climate change <span class="citation" data-cites="LewandowskyAliceWonderlandMechanics2016 LeiserowitzGlobalWarmingSix2021">(Lewandowsky, Cook, and Lloyd 2016; Leiserowitz et al. 2021)</span>; and how well political representatives understand the views and preferences of their constituents <span class="citation" data-cites="BolsenCitizensScientistsPolicy2015 Hertel-FernandezLegislativeStaffRepresentation2019">(Bolsen, Druckman, and Cook 2015; Hertel-Fernandez, Mildenberger, and Stokes 2019)</span>. Taken together, this body of work supports a model on which there is strong public support for climate policy, even among Republican/conservative voters, but that the fossil fuel industry’s propaganda efforts have succeeded in creating the misleading appearance of scientific and public controversy, what <span class="citation" data-cites="SparkmanAmericansExperienceFalse2022">Sparkman, Geiger, and Weber (2022)</span> call a “false social reality: a near universal perception of public opinion that is the opposite of true public sentiment.”</p>
<p>Much like using physical climate models to model future flood risks <span class="citation" data-cites="ParkerIncorporatingUserValues2019 LuskPoliticalLegitimacyDemocratic2020">(Parker and Lusk 2019; Lusk 2020)</span>, this body of social scientific-humanistic climate research is useful without claiming priority over other concerns. By understanding key actors and constituencies in the climate controversy, policymakers can design policies that are more likely to gather the support of broad coalitions. For example, a distinct feature of Ocasio-Cortez and Markey’s 2019 Green New Deal resolution was its call for a “just transition,” enabling fossil fuel workers to gradually move into other industries or take early retirement. These ideas played a significant role in the 2021 American Jobs Plan <span class="citation" data-cites="SicotteWillGreenNew2021">(Sicotte 2021)</span>, and thereby influenced the Bipartisan Infrastructure Bill.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-BolsenCitizensScientistsPolicy2015" class="csl-entry">
Bolsen, Toby, James N. Druckman, and Fay Lomax Cook. 2015. <span>“Citizens’, Scientists’, and Policy Advisors’ Beliefs about Global Warming.”</span> <em>The ANNALS of the American Academy of Political and Social Science</em> 658 (1): 271–95. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0002716214558393">https://doi.org/10.1177/0002716214558393</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-BrownDemocraticControlScientific2013" class="csl-entry">
Brown, Matthew J. 2013. <span>“The Democratic Control of the Scientific Control of Politics.”</span> In <em>The European Philosophy of Science Association Proceedings</em>, edited by Vassilios Karakostas and Dennis Dieks, 2:479–91. Springer International Publishing. <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-01306-0_39">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-01306-0_39</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-CartwrightEvidenceBasedPolicyPractical2012" class="csl-entry">
Cartwright, Nancy, and Jeremy Hardie. 2012. <em>Evidence-Based Policy: A Practical Guide to Doing It Better</em>. Oxford University Press. <a href="http://books.google.ca/books?id=kN3OdpkUyTcC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=intitle:Evidence+Based+Policy+A+Practical+Guide+to+Doing+It+Better&amp;hl=&amp;cd=1&amp;source=gbs_api">http://books.google.ca/books?id=kN3OdpkUyTcC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=intitle:Evidence+Based+Policy+A+Practical+Guide+to+Doing+It+Better&amp;hl=&amp;cd=1&amp;source=gbs_api</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-DouglasSciencePolicyValuefree2009" class="csl-entry">
Douglas, Heather E. 2009. <em>Science, Policy, and the Value-Free Ideal</em>. Pittsburgh, Pa: University of Pittsburgh Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-FeyerabendHowDefendSociety1975" class="csl-entry">
Feyerabend, Paul. 1975. <span>“How to Defend Society Against Science.”</span> <em>Radical Philosophy</em>, no. 011 (Summer): 3–8.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hertel-FernandezLegislativeStaffRepresentation2019" class="csl-entry">
Hertel-Fernandez, Alexander, Matto Mildenberger, and Leah C. Stokes. 2019. <span>“Legislative Staff and Representation in Congress.”</span> <em>American Political Science Review</em> 113 (1): 1–18. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0003055418000606">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0003055418000606</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksEpistemologicalDepthGM2015" class="csl-entry">
Hicks, Daniel J. 2015. <span>“Epistemological Depth in a GM Crops Controversy.”</span> <em>Studies in History and Philosophy of Science Part C: Studies in History and Philosophy of Biological and Biomedical Sciences</em> 50 (April): 1–12. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.shpsc.2015.02.002">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.shpsc.2015.02.002</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksGeneticallyModifiedCrops2017" class="csl-entry">
———. 2017. <span>“Genetically Modified Crops, Inclusion, and Democracy.”</span> <em>Perspectives on Science</em> 25 (4): 488–520. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/POSC_a_00251">https://doi.org/10.1162/POSC_a_00251</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LaceyScientificResearchTechnological2014" class="csl-entry">
Lacey, Hugh. 2014. <span>“Scientific Research, Technological Innovation and the Agenda of Social Justice, Democratic Participation and Sustainability.”</span> <em>Scientiae Studia</em> 12 (SPE): 37–55. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1590/S1678-31662014000400003">https://doi.org/10.1590/S1678-31662014000400003</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LeiserowitzGlobalWarmingSix2021" class="csl-entry">
Leiserowitz, Anthony, Connie Roser-Renouf, Jennifer Marlon, and Edward Maibach. 2021. <span>“Global Warming’s Six Americas: A Review and Recommendations for Climate Change Communication.”</span> <em>Current Opinion in Behavioral Sciences</em>, Human Response to Climate Change: From Neurons to Collective Action, 42 (December): 97–103. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cobeha.2021.04.007">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cobeha.2021.04.007</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LewandowskyAliceWonderlandMechanics2016" class="csl-entry">
Lewandowsky, Stephan, John Cook, and Elisabeth Lloyd. 2016. <span>“The <span>‘Alice in Wonderland’</span> Mechanics of the Rejection of (Climate) Science: Simulating Coherence by Conspiracism.”</span> <em>Synthese</em>, September, 1–22. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11229-016-1198-6">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11229-016-1198-6</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LloydModelRobustnessConfirmatory2015" class="csl-entry">
Lloyd, Elisabeth A. 2015. <span>“Model Robustness as a Confirmatory Virtue: The Case of Climate Science.”</span> <em>Studies in History and Philosophy of Science Part A</em> 49 (February): 58–68. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.shpsa.2014.12.002">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.shpsa.2014.12.002</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LonginoCanThereBe1987" class="csl-entry">
Longino, Helen E. 1987. <span>“Can There Be A Feminist Science?”</span> <em>Hypatia</em> 2 (3): 51–64. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1527-2001.1987.tb01341.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1527-2001.1987.tb01341.x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LuskPoliticalLegitimacyDemocratic2020" class="csl-entry">
Lusk, Greg. 2020. <span>“Political Legitimacy in the Democratic View: The Case of Climate Services.”</span> <em>Philosophy of Science</em>, July. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/710803">https://doi.org/10.1086/710803</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-OreskesMerchantsDoubtHow2011" class="csl-entry">
Oreskes, Naomi, and Erik M. Conway. 2011. <em>Merchants of Doubt: How a Handful of Scientists Obscured the Truth on Issues from Tobacco Smoke to Global Warming</em>. New York, NY, USA: Bloomsbury.
</div>
<div id="ref-ParkerIncorporatingUserValues2019" class="csl-entry">
Parker, Wendy S., and Greg Lusk. 2019. <span>“Incorporating User Values into Climate Services.”</span> <em>Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society</em> 100 (9): 1643–50. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-D-17-0325.1">https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-D-17-0325.1</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-SarewitzHowScienceMakes2004" class="csl-entry">
Sarewitz, Daniel. 2004. <span>“How Science Makes Environmental Controversies Worse.”</span> <em>Environmental Science and Policy</em> 7 (5): 385–403. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2004.06.001">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2004.06.001</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-SicotteWillGreenNew2021" class="csl-entry">
Sicotte, Diane. 2021. <span>“Will the Green New Deal Bring About a <span>‘Just Transition,’</span> or Just Transition? - American Sociological Association.”</span> Summer 2021. <a href="https://www.asanet.org/footnotes-article/will-green-new-deal-bring-about-just-transition-or-just-transition/">https://www.asanet.org/footnotes-article/will-green-new-deal-bring-about-just-transition-or-just-transition/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-SparkmanAmericansExperienceFalse2022" class="csl-entry">
Sparkman, Gregg, Nathan Geiger, and Elke U. Weber. 2022. <span>“Americans Experience a False Social Reality by Underestimating Popular Climate Policy Support by Nearly Half.”</span> <em>Nature Communications</em> 13 (1): 4779. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-32412-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-32412-y</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-SupranAssessingExxonMobilClimate2017" class="csl-entry">
Supran, Geoffrey, and Naomi Oreskes. 2017. <span>“Assessing ExxonMobil’s Climate Change Communications (1977–2014).”</span> <em>Environmental Research Letters</em> 12 (8): 084019. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/aa815f">https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/aa815f</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-04-07-pluralism-problems.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Nature endorsement and the value-free ideal</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-03-22-endorsement.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In October 2020, <em>Nature</em> published an editorial endorsing Joe Biden and criticizing Trump <span class="citation" data-cites="WhyNatureSupports2020">(<span>“Why Nature Supports Joe Biden for US President”</span> 2020)</span>. A few days ago, <em>Nature Human Behavior</em> published an online survey experimental study <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">(Zhang 2023)</span> that appeared to find that “some who saw the endorsement lost confidence in the journal as a result” <span class="citation" data-cites="LupiaPoliticalEndorsementsCan2023">(Lupia 2023)</span>. The study has prompted a lot of discussion on social media, especially after the editors of <em>Nature</em> stood by their decision to endorse Biden <span class="citation" data-cites="ShouldNatureEndorse2023">(<span>“Should Nature Endorse Political Candidates? Yes — When the Occasion Demands It”</span> 2023)</span> and Holden Thorp, editor-in-chief of <em>Science</em>, posted <a href="https://twitter.com/hholdenthorp/status/1638203875160104961">a short Twitter thread</a> in agreement.</p>
<p>In many of these discussions, <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> is being interpreted in terms of <a href="https://twitter.com/KevinZollman/status/1638542905018306560">the value-free ideal (VFI)</a>. This interpretation is mistaken, because the <em>Nature</em> endorsement doesn’t violate VFI. It does violate a more general principle, but by putting <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> in the context of my own empirical research I argue that violations of this principle don’t explain the headline findings. I develop a better explanation using another branch of my research, developing the “aims approach” to values in science.</p>
<section id="a-little-background-on-me" class="level1">
<h1>A little background on me</h1>
<p>Since I plan to share links to this post in social media threads with strangers, I thought it would be helpful to introduce myself and explain my expertise in this topic. I’m a philosopher of science and STS (science and technology studies) researcher at the University of California, Merced. As a philosopher of science I specialize in the subfield we call “science, values, and policy” or “science and values.” I’ve written <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7945-4416">a number of papers</a> on the value-free ideal, why almost all contemporary philosophers of science reject it, and the implications this has for policy-based science. My work experience includes two years as a AAAS Science and Technology Policy Fellow, during which I worked at<sup>1</sup> the US Environmental Protection Agency and the National Science Foundation. I also conduct empirical research, and recently published a collaboration with a cognitive psychologist that I’m going to discuss more below <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">(Hicks and Lobato 2022)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-nature-endorsement-doesnt-violate-vfi" class="level1">
<h1>The <em>Nature</em> endorsement doesn’t violate VFI</h1>
<p>My first point is that neither the <em>Nature</em> endorsement nor the summary seen by the participants in <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> violates VFI. The endorsement’s argument is straightforwardly political: Trump has made bad policy decisions, and Biden will make better ones.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>No US president in recent history has so relentlessly attacked and undermined so many valuable institutions, from science agencies to the media, the courts, the Department of Justice — and even the electoral system. Trump claims to put ‘America First’. But in his response to the pandemic, Trump has put himself first, not America. <span class="citation" data-cites="WhyNatureSupports2020">(<span>“Why Nature Supports Joe Biden for US President”</span> 2020)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Philosophers of science define the value-free ideal strictly, as a norm prohibiting the influence of non-epistemic values<sup>2</sup> in the “core” stages of scientific inquiry, especially the evaluation of hypotheses. While the <em>Nature</em> endorsement does make some claims that could be evaluated empirically as hypotheses, it’s not doing this empirical evaluation itself. Instead these claims are presented as premises in its argument that Trump has made bad policy decisions. So, there’s no violation of VFI here.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> provided the participants (specifically, the ones in the intervention arm of the study) with this summary of the endorsement:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>Scientific journal <em>Nature</em> endorsed Joe Biden</strong></p>
<p>Weeks before the 2020 presidential election, <strong><em>Nature</em></strong>’s editorial board official endorsed Joe Biden, citing:</p>
<ul>
<li>Donald Trump’s pandemic response had been “disastrous”;</li>
<li>Biden, unlike Trump, would listen to science, and thus;</li>
<li>Biden would handle the COVID-19 pandemic better.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em>Nature</em></strong> is one of the most-cited and most prestigious peer-reviewed scientific journals in the world.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> also included a screenshot of the endorsement headline and a link to the story. This summary also does not include a VFI violation.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-nature-endorsement-does-violate-value-neutrality-if-it-applies" class="level1">
<h1>The <em>Nature</em> endorsement does violate value neutrality (if it applies)</h1>
<p>The <em>Nature</em> endorsement doesn’t violate VFI, but it does seem to violate a more general norm, <strong>value neutrality</strong>. Havstad and Brown give a nice definition in their analysis of the IPCC’s ambition to be “policy-relevant but policy-neutral”:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>When making value judgments, parties who are objective in the sense of value-neutrality remain as neutral as possible where values are controversial, either by avoiding value judgments in that specific instance or by seeking balanced or conciliatory positions within the range of values. <span class="citation" data-cites="HavstadNeutralityRelevancePrescription2017 DouglasIrreducibleComplexityObjectivity2004">(Havstad and Brown 2017; see also H. Douglas 2004, 460)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Endorsing a candidate in a contested election is pretty much certain to involve controversial values.<sup>3</sup> So the endorsement obviously violated this neutrality norm.</p>
<p>However, we might question whether value neutrality applies to the <em>Nature</em> editors <em>in their role as editors</em>. I take it that many people think value neutrality applies to journalists in their role as journalists, but also that <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2020/09/28/editorial-board-endorsement-joe-biden/">newspaper endorsements of candidates</a> are not regarded objectionable. This would mean that the value neutrality norm applies to journalists as journalists, but not as editors (perhaps with restrictions, for example, to clearly-labelled opinion pieces).</p>
<p>Since <em>Nature</em> is a science journal, its editors are likely to be thought of as scientists (I’m too lazy to check to what extent its editors do in fact have scientific backgrounds, and in any case I expect editing the journal is sufficiently demanding that they’re not doing much actual research), and I take it most people think value neutrality applies to scientists. Still, for the endorsement to violate value neutrality, the scope of the norm would have to be broader for scientists than for journalists.</p>
<p>Value neutrality might be confused for VFI because the former entails the latter, at least so long as we assume (<a href="https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-01-30-democracy-defense.html">incorrectly</a>) “that epistemic values are politically neutral while non-epistemic values are politically controversial” and that value neutrality applies to scientists in the “core” stages of inquiry.</p>
<p><em>Should</em> value neutrality apply to scientists in their roles as journal editors writing a clearly-labelled opinion piece? Given that this norm doesn’t apply to newspaper editors, I can’t think of a compelling reason to apply it to scientific journal editors. There are also the critiques of neutrality given by <span class="citation" data-cites="HavstadNeutralityRelevancePrescription2017">Havstad and Brown (2017)</span>; and because value neutrality (plus assumptions) entails VFI, the many compelling arguments against VFI also apply to value neutrality (unless one tries to preserve it by rejecting some of the assumptions instead).<sup>4</sup> Though perhaps the results of <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> give us a consequentialist argument for applying the norm to scientists in their roles as journal editors: violating value neutrality undermines public trust in science.</p>
</section>
<section id="zhangpoliticalendorsementnature2023-findings-and-a-concern-about-generalizability" class="level1">
<h1><span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span>: Findings and a concern about generalizability</h1>
<p>So let’s turn to <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span>. The headline finding — as communicated with some really bad data visualization — was that Trump voters who saw the <em>Nature</em> endorsement summary in the experiment rated <em>Nature</em> editors as much less informed and much more biased, compared to Trump voters in the control condition. Treating the five-point Likert scale as a continuous one, the treatment effect was about -0.9 for informed and 0.6 for biased; that is, about a full point drop for informed and more than half a point for biased. Trump voters who saw the endorsement were also substantially less likely to get covid-19 information from <em>Nature</em>, again compared to Trump voters in the control condition.<sup>5</sup> Importantly, these effects were only observed for Trump voters. <strong>There was no sign of similar effects for Biden voters.</strong></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://media.nature.com/lw767/magazine-assets/d41586-023-00799-3/d41586-023-00799-3_24644262.png?as=webp" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The headline finding of <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span>: Trump voters who saw the <em>Nature</em> endorsement summary in the experiment rated <em>Nature</em> editors as much less informed and much more biased. I can’t get over how awful this visualization is. Source: <span class="citation" data-cites="LupiaPoliticalEndorsementsCan2023">Lupia (2023)</span></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Much of the commentary around <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> is generalizing this headline finding, to a claim that the endorsement undermined trust in science generally. <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> did examine this generalization, and did find statistically significant results for Trump voters. However, these effects were much smaller in magnitude, about 0.15 on the five-point Likert scale. This means that a few Trump voters saw science generally as a little less trustworthy after seeing the endorsement, but overall this effect is negligible. An old complaint in statistics is that “practical significance is different from statistical significance.”</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> would still be worrisome, insofar as one is worried that violations of neutrality could undermine trust in individual or well-defined groups of scientists (eg, the IPCC). But I don’t think we need to worry about the <em>Nature</em> endorsement undermining trust in science in general.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-zhangpoliticalendorsementnature2023-results-arent-explained-by-vfi-or-neutrality-violations" class="level1">
<h1>The <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> results aren’t explained by VFI or neutrality violations</h1>
<p>My overall claim in this post is that <strong>violations of neither VFI nor neutrality provide a good explanation of the findings of <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span></strong>. The first argument against VFI is that, as I discussed above, the endorsement doesn’t violate VFI. It’s hard to use a norm violation to explain these findings if the norm wasn’t violation. We could make a similar argument against a neutrality-based explanation if it turned out that most people (or Trump voters specifically) don’t think this norm applies to science journal editors when writing clearly-labelled opinion pieces.</p>
<p>I doubt that will be a compelling argument to many readers, though. My second argument starts by noting that there was no effect for Biden voters. If VFI and/or value neutrality violations explained these findings, we would expect to see effects for both Trump and Biden voters. But we don’t, so they don’t.</p>
<p>One potential response to this argument would be to posit an interaction model, on which the norm is evaluated differently by Trump vs.&nbsp;Biden voters. <a href="https://twitter.com/KevinZollman/status/1638542905018306560">Matt Weiner and Kevin Zollman</a> gave versions of this response on Twitter, in a thread started by João Ohara. In particular, my reading of Zollman’s version is that <em>VFI applies if and only if the scientist does not share one’s values</em>. So, for Trump voters, the <em>Nature</em> editors don’t share the participant’s values, so VFI applies, and so the <em>Nature</em> editors violated VFI. On the other hand, for Biden voters, the <em>Nature</em> editors <em>do</em> share the participant’s values, so VFI does <em>not</em> apply, and so the <em>Nature</em> editors <em>did not</em> violate VFI. Call this the <strong>shared values VFI model</strong>. (For the reasons given above, we should probably focus on a neutrality version of this explanation, rather than VFI. However, for simplicity, throughout the rest of the post I’m often going to use VFI as an umbrella term that includes neutrality.)</p>
<p>It would be difficult to study empirically whether and how VFI was playing a role in participants’ reactions to the endorsement. It wouldn’t be enough to simply ask participants whether they accept VFI (written in a way that a general audience can understand) and then run the same experiment as <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span>, because that wouldn’t get at the question of whether and how the participants are reasoning with VFI when they encounter the endorsement. There would also be a serious risk of priming effects, whichever order the questions were presented: seeing VFI first might make participants more likely to use it to react to the endorsement, while seeing the endorsement first might change their acceptance of VFI insofar as they see it as supporting or challenging their reaction to the endorsement. Qualitative methods — having participants narrate their reasoning about the endorsement, either out loud or in writing — could actually get at whether and how VFI is playing a role without worrying about priming. Though these methods are extremely labor intensive. None of this is a reason to think the shared values VFI model is false, of course. But it is reason to think this model is not pursuitworthy, which in turn is a reason to not accept it.</p>
</section>
<section id="conflicting-results-from-hicksvaluesdisclosurestrust2022" class="level1">
<h1>Conflicting results from <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span></h1>
<p>Another problem with the shared values VFI model for the findings of <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> is it conflicts with the results of a pair of extremely similar studies, <span class="citation" data-cites="ElliottValuesEnvironmentalResearch2017">Elliott et al. (2017)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span>. The latter paper is an independent replication of the former, using the same experimental design but a larger sample (slightly under 500 vs.&nbsp;slightly under 1,000 participants) from a more reliable pool (Amazon Mechanical Turk vs.&nbsp;a representative sample of US adults from the polling firm Prolific).</p>
<p>In both studies, participants were told that bisphenol A (BPA) is a controversial chemical, and shown a slide attributed to a (fictional) scientist, Dr.&nbsp;Riley Spence. The contents of the side differed by condition; here’s one example:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>My conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Protecting public health</em></strong> should be a top national priority.</li>
<li>I examined the scientific evidence on potential health risks of BPA.</li>
<li>I conclude that BPA in consumer products is <strong><em>causing harm</em></strong> to people.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>The first bullet point had three possibilities: either “protecting public health” (in this case), “promoting economic growth,” or this bullet was missing entirely. The third bullet had two possibilities, either “causing harm” (in this case) or “not causing harm.”<sup>6</sup> Participants then filled out the Muenster Epistemic Trustworthiness Inventory <span class="citation" data-cites="HendriksMeasuringLaypeopleTrust2015">(METI; Hendriks, Kienhues, and Bromme 2015)</span> to assess the perceived trustworthiness of Dr.&nbsp;Spence.<sup>7</sup> Participants were also asked for their own views on the tradeoff between public health and economic growth.</p>
<p>Hopefully it’s obvious how similar this study design is to <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span>; they’re so similar I’m a little disappointed that neither paper was cited! Both designs have a clear violation of neutrality. <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> does have a much larger sample size (over 4,000 participants) than either of the Riley Spence design studies. But in every other respect I think the Riley Spence design is better for examining the effects of violations of VFI or neutrality: the value judgments are stated explicitly, rather than implied by partisan alignment; those values have a clear partisan valence but the topic isn’t emotionally heated (this will be important in the next section); and the conclusion is a scientific claim rather than a political one.<sup>8</sup> The one major limitation in the Riley Spence design is that this isn’t an unambiguous violation of VFI; though to me including a value statement on the concluding slide of a presentation does implicate a VFI violation. And of course the prompt in <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> doesn’t include a violation of VFI either.</p>
<p>An additional, important advantage of the Riley Spence design is that it can distinguish shared values from the “first order” value held by the participant (whether the participant prioritizes public health or economic growth). This means this design can test a version of the shared values VFI model. We examine a “shared values” effect: given that the scientist discloses values, then “if the participant and scientist share the same values, the scientist is perceived as more trustworthy than if the participant and scientist do not share the same values” <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">(Hicks and Lobato 2022, 05)</span>. This doesn’t get at <em>why</em> shared values have this different effect — whether the participant is using VFI conditional on shared values or doing something else — but it does allow us to look for a shared values effect independent of which values the participant holds. Because <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> doesn’t have a Republican values arm, it can’t separate these potential effects.</p>
<p>Two findings of <span class="citation" data-cites="ElliottValuesEnvironmentalResearch2017">Elliott et al. (2017)</span> would seem to support <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> and the alternative explanation: they report a loss of perceived trust for a scientist who discloses values, compared to one who does not; and a shared values effect. However, <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span> does not find evidence for either effect, and shows that the shared values finding was an artifact of the unusual analytic approach taken by <span class="citation" data-cites="ElliottValuesEnvironmentalResearch2017 HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Elliott et al. (2017; Hicks and Lobato 2022, 10)</span>.</p>
<p>Consider first a reduction in trust for violating neutrality and disclosing a value judgment. <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span>’s estimate for this effect (for the “informed” item) is -0.85 on a 5-point scale (95% CI roughly -0.75 to -0.95), which would be about -1.19 (-1.05 to -1.33) if we (crudely) rescaled to the 7-point scales used in both the Riley Spence papers. <span class="citation" data-cites="ElliottValuesEnvironmentalResearch2017">Elliott et al. (2017)</span>’s data gives an estimate of -0.5 (-.3, -0.8), and <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span> estimate (0.0, -0.3). The more careful Riley Spence design yields much smaller effects than the design in <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span>. I’ll come back to the question of how we might explain differences in these estimates in the final section.</p>
<p>Suppose we side with <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> (despite the lower-quality design) and <span class="citation" data-cites="ElliottValuesEnvironmentalResearch2017">Elliott et al. (2017)</span> (despite the smaller and lower-quality sample) over <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span>, and judge that the total evidence favors an decline of trust from violating neutrality. Might an interaction between shared values and VFI be at work here? Again, <span class="citation" data-cites="ElliottValuesEnvironmentalResearch2017">Elliott et al. (2017)</span> report a shared values effect. But <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span> show that, when their data are re-analyzed using a more conventional method, there is no evidence of such an effect. What’s more, the data from both of these papers do support a “scientist values” effect: given that the scientist discloses values (violates neutrality), a scientist who values public health is perceived as more trustworthy than one who values economic growth, <em>even by participants who prioritize economic growth</em>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.frontiersin.org/files/Articles/1017362/fcomm-07-1017362-HTML/image_m/fcomm-07-1017362-g006.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A key finding from <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span>: There is no shared values effect, but instead a “scientist values” effect: a scientist who values public health is perceived as more trustworthy than one who values economic growth, even by participants who value economic growth. Panels correspond to participant values (relatively few participants valued economic growth), and columns within panels correspond to scientist values. In red, the vertical bars indicate the mean and 95% confidence interval, and comparisons between scientist value conditions are connected with a thin line. The “scientist values” effect is shown by the increase in the thin line. This is a much better data visualization: better contrast with the background, showing the individual observations, and highlighting the comparison of interest.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Because the Riley Spence design can separate shared and partisan values, while the design in <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> cannot, I think the Riley Spence design provides much more relevant and reliable evidence regarding a shared values VFI model. And so I think the findings from <span class="citation" data-cites="ElliottValuesEnvironmentalResearch2017">Elliott et al. (2017)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span> are a major challenge to that model.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-aims-of-science" class="level1">
<h1>The aims of science</h1>
<p>Based on study quality features, I think <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span> provides the strongest evidence among the three studies I’ve reviewed here; and this study finds evidence against both the “simple” VFI model and the more complex shared values VFI model. Of course I have a conflict of interest, and rather than simply declaring <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span> the “winner” a better approach would be to develop a model that can explain why <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span> produced different results <span class="citation" data-cites="DouglasWeighingComplexEvidence2012">(Heather Douglas 2012)</span>.</p>
<p>Following the discussion in <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span>, I suggest that the “aims approach” to values in science can provide a model that explains all of the results. On this approach, we start by recognizing that scientific research typically has a mix of epistemic and practical aims. For example, the aim of environmental epidemiology is not just to <em>understand</em> how pollution harms human health, but also to develop <em>policies</em> that reduce pollution and its health impacts. Proponents of this approach argue that the practical aims can play legitimate roles in all stages of scientific inquiry, even when evaluating hypotheses <span class="citation" data-cites="FernandezPintoLegitimizingValuesRegulatory2019 HicksWhenVirtuesAre2022">(Fernández Pinto and Hicks 2019; Hicks 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022">Hicks and Lobato (2022)</span>, we use this approach to explain the scientist values effect. We posit that almost all participants — even ones who prioritize economic growth — recognize protecting public health as one of the aims of environmental public health, while promoting economic growth is <em>not</em> among its aims. So a scientist who prioritizes public health is acting appropriately, while a scientist who prioritizes economic growth is not, regardless of the participant’s own priorities.</p>
<p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span>, I suggest that Trump and Biden voters saw the implied aims of the <em>Nature</em> editors very differently. Again, in the summary of the endorsement, the argument for endorsing Biden was that “Donald Trump’s pandemic response had been ‘disastrous’”; “Biden, unlike Trump, would listen to science”; and “Biden would handle the COVID-19 pandemic better.” I suggest that, for Biden voters, this argument communicated the legitimate scientific aim of informing public policy to promote public health. On the other hand, I suggest that many Trump voters would read this argument as scientists trying to shift blame from scientific authorities (CDC, NIH) to Trump, calling for even more power and influence than they already have, and trying to justify policies that these voters saw as creeping authoritarianism (stay-at-home orders, restrictions on restaurants and other businesses, mask and vaccination requirements). None of these are legitimate scientific aims.</p>
<p>On this model, shared values don’t play a role in any of these studies. The participants’ values (more properly, the participants’ epistemic community and their interpretive frames) can play a role, but early on, when the participant reads the stimulus. But then it’s the scientist’s values that matter, and whether those values align or conflict with the aims of science, not whether the align or conflict with the participants’ values.</p>
<p>And neither neutrality nor VFI play a role in this model. The aims approach has been developed as an alternative to VFI (and neutrality), to explain how scientists legitimately use non-epistemic values throughout their research.</p>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-DouglasIrreducibleComplexityObjectivity2004" class="csl-entry">
Douglas, H. 2004. <span>“The Irreducible Complexity of Objectivity.”</span> <em>Synthese</em> 138 (3): 453–73. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1023/B:SYNT.0000016451.18182.91">https://doi.org/10.1023/B:SYNT.0000016451.18182.91</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-DouglasWeighingComplexEvidence2012" class="csl-entry">
Douglas, Heather. 2012. <span>“Weighing Complex Evidence in a Democratic Society.”</span> <em>Kennedy Institute of Ethics Journal</em> 22 (2).
</div>
<div id="ref-ElliottValuesEnvironmentalResearch2017" class="csl-entry">
Elliott, Kevin C., Aaron M. McCright, Summer Allen, and Thomas Dietz. 2017. <span>“Values in Environmental Research: Citizens’ Views of Scientists Who Acknowledge Values.”</span> <em>PLOS ONE</em> 12 (10): e0186049. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0186049">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0186049</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-FernandezPintoLegitimizingValuesRegulatory2019" class="csl-entry">
Fernández Pinto, Manuela, and Daniel J. Hicks. 2019. <span>“Legitimizing Values in Regulatory Science.”</span> <em>Environmental Health Perspectives</em> 127 (3): 035001. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP3317">https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP3317</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HavstadNeutralityRelevancePrescription2017" class="csl-entry">
Havstad, Joyce C., and Matthew J. Brown. 2017. <span>“Neutrality, Relevance, Prescription, and the IPCC.”</span> <em>Public Affairs Quarterly</em> 31 (4): 303–24. <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/44732800">https://www.jstor.org/stable/44732800</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HendriksMeasuringLaypeopleTrust2015" class="csl-entry">
Hendriks, Friederike, Dorothe Kienhues, and Rainer Bromme. 2015. <span>“Measuring Laypeople’s Trust in Experts in a Digital Age: The Muenster Epistemic Trustworthiness Inventory (METI).”</span> <em>PLOS ONE</em> 10 (10): e0139309. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0139309">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0139309</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksWhenVirtuesAre2022" class="csl-entry">
Hicks, Daniel J. 2022. <span>“When Virtues are Vices: <span>‘Anti-Science’</span> Epistemic Values in Environmental Politics.”</span> <em>Philosophy, Theory, and Practice in Biology</em> 14 (0). <a href="https://doi.org/10.3998/.2629">https://doi.org/10.3998/.2629</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-HicksValuesDisclosuresTrust2022" class="csl-entry">
Hicks, Daniel J., and Emilio Jon Christopher Lobato. 2022. <span>“Values Disclosures and Trust in Science: A Replication Study.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Communication</em> 7. <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fcomm.2022.1017362">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fcomm.2022.1017362</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-LupiaPoliticalEndorsementsCan2023" class="csl-entry">
Lupia, Arthur. 2023. <span>“Political Endorsements Can Affect Scientific Credibility.”</span> <em>Nature</em> 615 (7953): 590–91. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-023-00799-3">https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-023-00799-3</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-SchroederDemocraticValuesBetter" class="csl-entry">
Schroeder, S. Andrew. n.d. <span>“Democratic Values: A Better Foundation for Public Trust in Science.”</span> <em>The British Journal for the Philosophy of Science</em>. Accessed June 29, 2019. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bjps/axz023">https://doi.org/10.1093/bjps/axz023</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ShouldNatureEndorse2023" class="csl-entry">
<span>“Should Nature Endorse Political Candidates? Yes — When the Occasion Demands It.”</span> 2023. <em>Nature</em> 615 (7953): 561–61. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-023-00789-5">https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-023-00789-5</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-WhyNatureSupports2020" class="csl-entry">
<span>“Why Nature Supports Joe Biden for US President.”</span> 2020. <em>Nature</em> 586 (7829): 335–35. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-020-02852-x">https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-020-02852-x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023" class="csl-entry">
Zhang, Floyd Jiuyun. 2023. <span>“Political Endorsement by Nature and Trust in Scientific Expertise During COVID-19.”</span> <em>Nature Human Behaviour</em>, March, 1–11. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-023-01537-5">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-023-01537-5</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Technically “at,” not “for.”↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>It’s common in the literature to use “non-epistemic values” interchangeably with something like “social and political values.” But I think this is incorrect, because — on my preferred definition of epistemic values, namely, features of scientific practice that promote the pursuit of epistemic aims such as truth and understanding — social and political values can sometimes be epistemic <span class="citation" data-cites="HicksWhenVirtuesAre2022">(Hicks 2022, esp.&nbsp;pages 1-2)</span>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>This is actually tricky in the <em>Nature</em> endorsement, because their value judgments are bundled into thick claims. For example, one of their premises is that Trump’s management of the pandemic was “disastrous.” This is a <em>thick concept</em>, with both descriptive criteria for application and evaluative implications: Trump’s handling of the pandemic resulted in hundreds of thousands of preventable deaths, and this is a severely bad thing. (Note that “preventable death” is another thick concept.) The controversy here isn’t over the evaluative side, the idea that preventable deaths are bad. Instead it’s over the descriptive side: that Trump’s handling of the pandemic had these effects.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Specifically, someone might try to concede VFI and preserve value neutrality by rejecting the alignment between epistemic/non-epistemic and neutral/controversial values. <span class="citation" data-cites="SchroederDemocraticValuesBetter">Schroeder (n.d.)</span> might potentially be read in this way: democratically-endorsed non-epistemic values are treated as not controversial, and so appealing to them does not violate neutrality.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>I’m confused by the scale used in reporting this effect, so I’m just calling it “substantial” here.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>Varying these independently means that we can distinguish any effects related to the value judgment from effects of the conclusion. The design in <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> can’t do this, because in a sense the value judgment <em>is</em> the conclusion.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>One incidental concern about <span class="citation" data-cites="ZhangPoliticalEndorsementNature2023">Zhang (2023)</span> is that they used a single item for every variable of interest. They did ask about two aspects of trustworthiness, whether the trustee was informed and whether they were biased. But that was done using exactly two questions, and responses weren’t combined. Psychologists seem to prefer multi-item instruments. For example, the METI has 14 items covering three aspects of trustworthiness: competence, benevolence, and integrity. I’m not entirely sure why psychologists prefer multi-item instruments, though, so I decided not to discuss it in the body of the post.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p><span class="citation" data-cites="ElliottValuesEnvironmentalResearch2017">Elliott et al. (2017)</span> report a second study with a policy conclusion, namely, whether BPA should be regulated. Due to limited funds my collaborator and I didn’t replicate this part.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-03-22-endorsement.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Constructivist accounts of representation, in science and politics</title>
  <dc:creator>Dan Hicks</dc:creator>
  <link>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-02-08-demagoguery.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Political theorists developed a <em>constructivist</em> approach to political representation around 2010; <span class="citation" data-cites="SawardRepresentativeClaim2010">Saward (2010)</span> seems to be the canonical citation for this approach, but I think <span class="citation" data-cites="BrownScienceDemocracyExpertise2009">M. B. Brown (2009)</span> is doing something quite similar. Prior to 2010, work by political theorists on representation focused on either (a) formal procedures of elections and voting or (b) deliberative practices, either in civil society (that is, outside of government) or in boundary institutions that connected public deliberation to policymakers. Recently several philosophers of science have picked up ideas from the latter (citations in <a href="2023-01-30-democracy-defense.html">a previous post</a>).</p>
<p>Constructivists challenge an implicit assumption of these approaches, namely, the there is a constituency or public that exists prior to representation and has more-or-less well-defined interests or preferences. This assumption might (<em>might</em>) make sense when we’re talking about legislative districts: the State of California existed before Diane Feinstein was first elected Senator in 1992. But it doesn’t work as well for less formal types of representation, for example, Martin Luther King, Jr., or Greta Thunberg as representatives of social movements.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="SawardRepresentativeClaim2010">Saward (2010)</span> apparently (I haven’t actually read the book) draws on Gricean philosophy of language that will be familiar to most philosophers today. Specifically, <span class="citation" data-cites="SawardRepresentativeClaim2010">Saward (2010)</span> examines representative claims as speech acts, claims that the speaker represents a certain public or constituency to an audience in a certain context and that this constituency believes or wants or does something. These acts are successful insofar as they are taken up by the audience. In other words, to be a representative for a constituency is nothing more or less than to be taken as a representative for that constituency.</p>
<p>Importantly, the constituency does not need to exist for a representative claim to be successful. One practical <em>effect</em> of the speech act might be that the constituency comes into existence as members of the audience identify themselves as members of that constituency. For example, what we now call the “MAGA movement” or “MAGA Republicans” didn’t exist until after Trump presented himself as a representative for that then-unnamed constituency in 2015. Drawing on Hobbes, <span class="citation" data-cites="BrownScienceDemocracyExpertise2009">M. B. Brown (2009)</span> calls this <em>virtual representation</em><sup>1</sup>, and he uses it to develop an account of (natural) scientists as representatives of nature in policy contexts. Even if it makes sense to talk about “nature” as a single coherent entity, that entity can’t do something like authorize a scientist as its representative through a formal election or have beliefs or interests that are accurately or inaccurately represented by a scientist’s representative claims.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="UrbinatiJudgmentAloneCloven2018">Urbinati (2018)</span> discusses this constructivist approach to political representation. I found her writing somewhat difficult to follow, so I’m not going to try to fully reconstruct her views. But she does seem to present three objections to constructivism:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>It neglects inequalities in who will make representative claims and whose representative claims will be taken up.<br>
</li>
<li>The representative is accountable to the audience rather than the constituency.<br>
</li>
<li>There’s no reason to think that successful representative claims (as constructivists understand that success) will have any effects on policy. <span class="citation" data-cites="UrbinatiJudgmentAloneCloven2018">(Urbinati 2018, 74ff)</span></li>
</ol>
<p>The first objection echoes <span class="citation" data-cites="YoungInclusionDemocracy2000">Young (2000)</span>’s critique of deliberative democracy, which (prior to Young’s critique) tended to focus on idealized deliberative scenarios and norms of deliberation that favored highly educated white men. The third objection seems to provide the best support for <span class="citation" data-cites="UrbinatiJudgmentAloneCloven2018">Urbinati (2018)</span>’s “diarchic” approach, which emphasizes the relationship between formal institutions of political power and the open-ended deliberation of civil society. (I suspect some of the later contributions to this collection will do this as well.)</p>
<p>On the “pre-constructivist” models of representation, representatives are primarily accountable to the constituency that they represent. This might be done formally — the representative needs to stand for (re)election — or it might happen informally — as constituents call representatives to give an account of their actions qua representatives.<sup>2</sup> Urbinati’s point seems to be that, by basing legitimacy on audience uptake, constructivists lose the demand for democratic accountability. Audience uptake matters, and representative and constituency co-construct each other (again, consider Trump), but <em>good</em> representatives must still represent their constituents <em>accurately</em>.</p>
<p>For <span class="citation" data-cites="BrownScienceDemocracyExpertise2009">M. B. Brown (2009)</span>, a constructivist account of scientific representation (scientists as representatives of nature) is attractive because democratic accountability to “nature” seems to be nonsensical.<sup>3</sup> So if scientists are to be held accountable to anyone besides themselves, the audience seems to be the only option.</p>
<p>In the context of Brown’s account, we might understand Urbinati’s second concern as a critique of “wishful thinking” or “anything-goes” relativism: nothing seems to be stopping the audience from rejecting scientists whose claims are inconvenient or unfavorable (no matter how well-supported), and accepting scientists whose claims are convenient and favorable (no matter how flimsy) <span class="citation" data-cites="SarewitzHowScienceMakes2004 SteelQualifiedEpistemicPriority2017 LichtensteinInconvenientTruthInductive2022">(Sarewitz 2004; Steel 2017; Lichtenstein 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>One constructivist response to this critique might be to reject the notion of accuracy, as in the formulation “good representatives must still represent their constituents accurately.” Such a constructivist might argue that “accuracy” assumes a pre-existing constituency; but representative claims are prior to constituencies, etc. On the science side, this leads to the interminable and fatally abstract debates over “realism” of the 1970s and ’80s.</p>
<p>An alternative approach might draw on Dewey’s account of inquiry, specifically as articulated by <span class="citation" data-cites="BrownScienceMoralImagination2020">M. Brown (2020)</span>. On this account, inquiry starts with a problematic situation — things aren’t working — and inquiry is successful insofar as it resolves the situation — develops alternative things that do work. Importantly, “working” here has both “realist” and “constructivist” aspects. It’s realist insofar as the agent can <em>incorrectly</em> believe that a certain alternative will work when “in fact” it will not. But it’s also constructivist insofar as one tactic to resolve the situation is for the agent to change their understanding of the activity and its goals, and resolving the situation does not require a “true” representation of the world (in a classical correspondence sense).<sup>4</sup></p>
<p>I suggest we can view political representation as “inquiry” using this account. The problematic situation is that some people<sup>5</sup> have some felt dissatisfaction with the status quo. A representative claim is then a hypothesis that there is a group (the constituency) whose interests are not being served by the policy status quo (the diagnosis), and that adopting a different policy will resolve the problematic situation (the remedy).</p>
<p>On this model, a representative claim will have locutionary success criteria, that is, it needs to be taken up by the audience, especially people with the power to enact the proposed policy. And the constituency can be constructed by the representative claim, insofar as the “some people” subsequently decide that they are indeed members of the group and their interests are not being served by the status quo. But <strong>the representative claim also has pragmatic success criteria</strong>: would the remedy actually resolve the problematic situation as characterized by the diagnosis? This is unlikely to be the case if, for example, there is good evidence that the felt dissatisfaction experienced by group members is not caused by the factors identified in the diagnosis.</p>
<p>Consider how this model might work for Trump’s 2016 campaign. We can reconstruct the central representative claim of Trump’s campaign as something like the hypothesis that rural poverty is caused by mass undocumented immigration and so strong immigration restrictions will solve this problem. This claim was taken up by the media, who did numerous profiles of “Trump voters” (the newly-constructed constituency) in impoverished rural areas and their attitudes towards immigration. So it was evidently a locutionary success. But its pragmatic success is tenuous at best; agricultural consolidation and demographic shifts (depopulation and aging as young adults go to college and move to urban areas) are probably much more important causes of rural poverty than immigration, undocumented or otherwise.</p>





<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-BrownScienceDemocracyExpertise2009" class="csl-entry">
Brown, Mark B. 2009. <em>Science in Democracy: Expertise, Institutions, and Representation</em>. Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-BrownScienceMoralImagination2020" class="csl-entry">
Brown, Matthew. 2020. <em>Science and Moral Imagination: A New Ideal for Values in Science</em>. University of Pittsburgh Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-LiboironPollutionColonialism2021" class="csl-entry">
Liboiron, Max. 2021. <em>Pollution Is Colonialism</em>. Duke University Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-LichtensteinInconvenientTruthInductive2022" class="csl-entry">
Lichtenstein, Eli I. 2022. <span>“Inconvenient Truth and Inductive Risk in Covid-19 Science.”</span> <em>Philosophy of Medicine</em> 3 (1). <a href="https://doi.org/10.5195/pom.2022.132">https://doi.org/10.5195/pom.2022.132</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-SarewitzHowScienceMakes2004" class="csl-entry">
Sarewitz, Daniel. 2004. <span>“How Science Makes Environmental Controversies Worse.”</span> <em>Environmental Science and Policy</em> 7 (5): 385–403. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2004.06.001">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2004.06.001</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-SawardRepresentativeClaim2010" class="csl-entry">
Saward, Michael. 2010. <em>The Representative Claim</em>. OUP Oxford.
</div>
<div id="ref-SimpsonLandPedagogyNishnaabeg2014" class="csl-entry">
Simpson, Leanne Betasamosake. 2014. <span>“Land as Pedagogy: Nishnaabeg Intelligence and Rebellious Transformation.”</span> <em>Decolonization: Indigeneity, Education &amp; Society</em> 3 (3). <a href="https://jps.library.utoronto.ca/index.php/des/article/view/22170">https://jps.library.utoronto.ca/index.php/des/article/view/22170</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-SteelQualifiedEpistemicPriority2017" class="csl-entry">
Steel, Daniel. 2017. <span>“Qualified Epistemic Priority.”</span> In <em>Current Controversies in Values and Science</em>, edited by Kevin C. Elliott and Daniel Steel, 49–63. New York and London: Routledge.
</div>
<div id="ref-UrbinatiJudgmentAloneCloven2018" class="csl-entry">
Urbinati, Nadia. 2018. <span>“Judgment Alone: Cloven Citizenship in the Era of the Internet.”</span> In <em>Creating Political Presence: The New Politics of Democratic Representation</em>, edited by Dario Castiglione and Johannes Pollak. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press. <a href="https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/C/bo29203064.html">https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/C/bo29203064.html</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-YoungInclusionDemocracy2000" class="csl-entry">
Young, Iris Marion. 2000. <em>Inclusion and Democracy</em>. Oxford University Press. <a href="http://books.google.ca/books?id=Gonp8GXTxb0C&amp;pg=PA18&amp;dq=intitle:INCLUSION+AND+DEMOCRACY+inauthor:young&amp;hl=&amp;cd=1&amp;source=gbs_api">http://books.google.ca/books?id=Gonp8GXTxb0C&amp;pg=PA18&amp;dq=intitle:INCLUSION+AND+DEMOCRACY+inauthor:young&amp;hl=&amp;cd=1&amp;source=gbs_api</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Or maybe “fictional representation”? Need to check.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Young cite here?↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Yesterday I was preparing <span class="citation" data-cites="SimpsonLandPedagogyNishnaabeg2014">Simpson (2014)</span> as a reading on Indigenous epistemology and land relations for the Environmental Philosophy course that I’m teaching this semester. From the perspective of Indigenous land relations, accountability to “nature” — or rather, nonhuman agents — does make sense. Indeed, as presented by various Indigenous authors <span class="citation" data-cites="SimpsonLandPedagogyNishnaabeg2014 LiboironPollutionColonialism2021">(Simpson 2014; Liboiron 2021)</span> a key idea in Indigenous knowledge-making practices is consent and collaboration with nonhuman agents. I’m going to bracket this thought for the purposes of this post.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Sorry Matt Brown, nobody else thinks Dewey was a correspondence theorist.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>This should be understood as a Boolosean plural quantifier: “there are some <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?x">s,” rather than “there is a set <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X">.”↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-copyright"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Copyright</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div>Dan Hicks</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dhicks.github.io/posts/2023-02-08-demagoguery.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
